<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true relation of the cruelties and barbarities of the French upon the English prisoners of war being a journal of their travels from Dinan in Britany, to Thoulon in Provence, and back again  ... / faithfully and impartially performed by Richard Strutton, being an eye-witness, and a fellow sufferer.</title>
            <author>Strutton, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 198 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61854</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S6018</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17656</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13038627</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13038627</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96857</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61854)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96857)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 400:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true relation of the cruelties and barbarities of the French upon the English prisoners of war being a journal of their travels from Dinan in Britany, to Thoulon in Provence, and back again  ... / faithfully and impartially performed by Richard Strutton, being an eye-witness, and a fellow sufferer.</title>
                  <author>Strutton, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 57, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Licens'd June 27, 1690. James Fraser"</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: [3] p. at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Strutton, Richard.</term>
               <term>Prisoners of war --  England.</term>
               <term>Prisoners of war --  France.</term>
               <term>Grand Alliance, War of the, 1689-1697 --  Prisoners and prisons, French.</term>
               <term>Grand Alliance, War of the, 1689-1697 --  Personal narratives, English.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Louis XIV, 1643-1715.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96857:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96857:1"/>
            <p>A TRUE RELATION OF THE <hi>Cruelties</hi> and <hi>Barbarities</hi> OF THE FRENCH, UPON THE ENGLISH PRISONERS of WAR.</p>
            <p>BEING A Journal of their TRAVELS from <hi>Dinan</hi> in <hi>Britany,</hi> to <hi>Thoulon</hi> in <hi>Provence:</hi> And back again.</p>
            <p>With a Deſcription of the Situation, and Fortifications of all the Eminent Towns upon the Road, and their Diſtance. Of their Priſons and Hoſpitals, and the Number of the Men that died under their Cruelty: With the Names of many of them, and the Places of their Deaths and Burials: With an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the great Charity and Sufferings of the Poor Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants of <hi>France:</hi> And other Material Things that hapned up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Way.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Faithfully and Impartially Performed by <hi>Richard Strutton,</hi> being an Eye-Witneſs, and a Fellow Sufferer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LICENS'D <hi>June</hi> 27. 1690.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>James Fraſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin,</hi> near the <hi>Black Bull</hi> in the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> MDCXC.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:96857:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96857:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Moſt Serene and Mighty PRINCESS, MARY, By the Grace of God, QUEEN of <hi>Great Britain, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Illuſtrious Princeſs,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>INCE God, the Fountain of all Goodneſs, hath given us Your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties moſt Sacred Perſons to Rule and Reign over us, to the great Joy of all thoſe that wiſh well to our <hi>Zion,</hi> and a Terror to the Diſaffected; I do humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech Your Majeſty out of the Abundance of Your wonted Clemency, That when Your Majeſties moſt weighty Matters ſhall give leiſure, that then Your Majeſty would be pleaſed to lend Your Gracious Ear to the Travels and Sorrows of Your Majeſties poor Subjects in <hi>France.</hi> So the great God above, by whoſe Power alone Monarchs Reign, Bleſs Your Majeſties with a Long and a Happy Reign over us, and Crown You with Glory Everlaſting.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>So Prays, Your Majeſties moſt Loyal, and Obedient Subject, <hi>RICHARD STR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TTON.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:96857:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96857:3"/>
            <head>TO THE <hi>Courteous Readers:</hi> Eſpecially to all SEA-FARING Men.</head>
            <p>AS it is neither uſual nor convenient to jump at once from the Title-page to the Matter, I ſhall therefore make this ſmall Digreſſion, not to tire your ears with Tautologies, or unneceſſary Trifles, but on the contrary, to give you an Account of the whole End and Scope of my Deſign in gathering together this ſmall Tractate of the Hard <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage of ſome of our Country-men in <hi>France,</hi> that whoſoever ſhall read this enſuing Relation, and will be pleaſed to compare it with the Actions of other Nations, may then give their Judgments in the general, whether or no this looks like the actions of Chriſtians or not, and of thoſe who ſtile themſelves of the better ſort. So that when you have had a clear view of ſome part of their work, you may the better judg the Artifices of the Workmen: That whenſoever it may fall in your way, as I doubt not but it will of many of you; then let me deſire you to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the words of the Law, <hi>(That whoſoever ſheddeth blood, by man ſhall his blood be ſhed)</hi> Many will be apt to ſay, That theſe words were ſignified by <hi>Moſes</hi> to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for the propagating of a Civil Government; yet notwithſtanding, we ſee that this Law hath been tranſlated and continued in all Ages, and amongſt the moſt Civilized people ſince that time; as for example, all thoſe under the Goſpel-Diſpenſation: Yet ſtill many will object and ſay, Theſe words are purely meant in caſe of wilful Murther: To all ſuch I ſhall humbly deſire, That they would be pleaſed to read, or elſe at leaſt to give ear to this enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Diary; wherein they will find the Manner and Method that was uſed by them, was to put men to the worſt of Deaths, <hi>(viz.)</hi> by Travelling, Beating, and alſo ſtarving them with Hunger and Cold; which is no leſs than wilful Murder; then pray let them judg whether their Deaths was not deſigned by them when this work was firſt cut out: True it is, <hi>Nero</hi> had his varieties of Deaths, which he was pleaſed to impoſe upon the Primitive Chriſtians in his time, for the which he became famous for Cruelty, and was juſtly ſtiled the Enemy of Mankind. But had <hi>Nero</hi> lived in theſe days, he might very well have been comented, before he commenced Maſter of Cruelty and Tyranny, to have become the Scholar of this <hi>Moſt Chriſtian Tyrant,</hi> who would have taught him better methods to have accompliſhed his moſt Bloody Deſign, and not have fallen one jot ſhort of it: For as <hi>Nero</hi> did delight to ſee thoſe innocent Chriſtians Blood ſpilt in ſport in his Theatres, as he did, at that time there was no Power upon Earth that was able to ſtop him in this his full Career of Blood, until the hand of Divine Juſtice had done it, and brought his miſery upon him at home, that he was forc'd to ſay, when he was ſo miſerable
<pb facs="tcp:96857:4"/>and forſaken of all Men, that he had not ſo much as a Man that would kill him upon his own requeſt: <hi>Nec amicum habeo, nec inimicum;</hi> i.e. <hi>I have never a Friend nor Enemy.</hi> Juſt ſo it had happened with us, the People of <hi>England,</hi> but that it pleaſed the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God of his great goodneſs to ſettle the Crown of theſe Kingdoms upon the Heads of this Royal Pair, <hi>William</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> in that mutable time when the very breath of the Factious had ſo much diſturbed the Air, that the Seas became dangerous to all that Navigated; that then they put a ſtop to the full Career of this Tyrant's Fury, whom nothing elſe muſt have ſerved, but a Sea of Innocent Blood. Then, ſince it hath ſo pleaſed God to avert that great Judgment which was hovering over this Land, which tended to no leſs than the abſolute Overthrow of both Church and State: and on the other ſide, hath given us a Nurſing-Father and Mother, to ſecure us ſafe under their ſhadow; let none of us therefore, <hi>Engliſh</hi>-men, whom the matter doth concern, that lay any Claim or Title to the Heroical Blood of the <hi>Britains,</hi> whoſe Valour hath formerly run through the whole World, and hath eclipſed the Glory of <hi>France</hi> more than once; let none therefore, that putteth his hand to this Plough, look back; eſpecially now they ſee the Examples of our Renowned Monarchs revived <hi>(viz.)</hi> thoſe of <hi>Edward</hi> III. and of <hi>Henry</hi> V. who to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem the dying Honour of <hi>England,</hi> expoſed themſelves to the greateſt dangers, and came not back empty-handed; for it is ſaid, <hi>Audentes fortuna juvat;</hi> i. e. <hi>Fortune helps the Bold.</hi> Let us therefore ſet God and the Goſpel's Purity before us; and let That be the chief Mark we aim at; and without doubt, by God's Aſſiſtance, we may eclipſe the Glory of <hi>Louis le Grand,</hi> as he is now ſtiled. I do not doubt but it will fare with my poor Endeavours in this Boook, as it hath fared with thoſe of ten thouſand times more worth, to be carp'd at by ſome of the Criticks of this Age, who can ſooner find Ten Faults in the Actions of another perſon, than mend one in themſelves. I have not one word to ſay in the praiſe of it, it being but a rough thing, and not ſo well poliſhed as if it had been done by a more skilful hand; and beſides, my great trouble and wearineſs of Body, when theſe things were collected together; my right-hand being chained, in which I held my Pen, for thirty ſeven days together: When all theſe things are conſidered rightly, it will render me the more excuſable. Yet I have this to ſay, Although it is not put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a lofty Stile, as might have been done by another Man; yet I am ſure that what is in it is ſo true, that it is able to contend with Truth it ſelf; and therefore I hope that Truth is not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed, although ſhe be but in a plain Dreſs. I ſhall therefore deſire you to take this notice as you read, for your better underſtanding of ſome particulars, which is not known to every Man: The <hi>Sirdena</hi> ſignifies a ſmall Fiſh, a little bigger than a Sprat; and as for <hi>Beverage,</hi> that is meant Vinegar and Water, or Wine and Water; <hi>Denires</hi> is alſo ſpoken of very often, which is the ſmall Money of that Country, of which Twelve makes one Souſe, or Penny <hi>Engliſh.</hi> So wiſhing you more pleaſure in the reading, than I had in the writing, I take my leave, and ſubſcribe my ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours in all Love,</hi>
                  <hi>Richard Strutton.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Deptford, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <date>June 21. 1690.</date>
                  </hi>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:96857:4"/>
            <head>A TRUE ACCOUNT OF THE <hi>Cruelties and Barbarities</hi> OF THE FRENCH, UPON THE ENGLISH Priſoners of WAR, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <hi>June</hi> 8. 1689.</p>
               <p>I Then being come from the <hi>Canaries,</hi> in the Ship <hi>Merry Frigat, Emanuel Dart</hi> Commander, right off <hi>Portland</hi> we met a Privateer of St. <hi>Malo;</hi> after what reſiſtance we could well make, many of our Men not ſhewing themſelves ſo valiant as did become <hi>Engliſh</hi>-Men, but on the contrary ran down into the Hold, and left the Commander, with only Three more, to fight this Privateer; which thing we did to our utmoſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, killing them ſeveral Men; Our Commander being dangerouſly wounded in the Shoulder, and the Gunner ſhot in the Leg, we were at laſt forced to yield to mercileſs Men, who, after we were taken, treated us like themſelves, by ſtrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us almoſt quite naked, and wounding ſeveral of the Men. The Eleventh of this Month they put us aſhore into the Priſon of St. <hi>Malo;</hi> the wounded were ſent to their Hoſpital. In this ſame filthy Priſon we remain'd until the 25th of <hi>July,</hi> and then they ſent about 180 of us to <hi>Roch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>July</hi> 25. 1689. <hi>die Jovis.</hi> About Ten in the morning came the <hi>Guard a Marine,</hi> with his Company, for to take us out of the Priſon of <hi>Dinan;</hi> he having a Roll of our Names, call'd us over two by two, and drove us into an Apartment, where
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96857:5"/>we were Hand-cuff'd two and two to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, with Hand-cuffs made of Leather, and ſo lock'd with a ſmall Padlock; That being in this manner done to us all, we Marched out of the Caſtle into the Town, where we found a Hundred or more of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> which were the ſame day brought from St. <hi>Malo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> all in the ſame order, Handcuff'd, two and two; we no ſooner met, but away we marched to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Rochfort</hi> in a moſt miſerable conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſome almoſt naked, and many bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot and bare-legg'd; in this manner we marched from <hi>Dinan</hi> to a Village call'd <hi>Bechereal,</hi> fourteen Miles diſtant; in this place they gave us that Victuals for Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per which we were to have had for Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in <hi>Dinan:</hi> As for our Liquor it was Water; ſo here we ſlept in the Stables, and in Barns, and many were forc'd to ſleep in the open Yard in ſome Hay that lay there.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Friday</hi> 26. In the morning before we ſet forth, ſeveral of our Men that were naked almoſt, Spun Hay Ropes, and ſo wrapped them about their Bodies, Legs, and Arms, to keep them from the cold by night,
<note place="margin">The Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuffs galling, the mens Hands were looſed many of them, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on promiſe of their walking quietly and orderly.</note> and the ſcorching of the Sun by day; after they had given us a ſmall bit of Bread and Butter, away we marched towards the City of <hi>Rhemes,</hi> Nineteen Miles di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant; as we were on the way, ſeveral of our Men fell lame, and could not travel; then were they forced to hire Carts for them. By the way we ſaw two Country-men at work in the Field, whom the <hi>Guard a Marine</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to fetch their Horſes to draw the Carts; the two Men ſeeing the Belt by which he commanded, ran away; they being in the Fields, and an high Bank be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, thought to get clear of them; but one of them diſmounted and ran after them, and ſo brought them into the Road, where the <hi>Guard a Marine</hi> drub'd them ſo long, that I believe he gave them at leaſt Fifty blows, ſo that I ſaw the Piſs run out of the Knees of the Breeches of one of them; and when that was done, he made each of them down on their Knees, and of them take a good luſty heavy Lad, and carry him upon his back at leaſt a M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le. When we came into the City, we were brought into a cloſe Yard belonging to an Inn, where we were ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with Bread and Water, and our Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was in the Stables, and many lay in the open yard, for want of room. The ſavage people many of them kept heaving of Stones over the Walls at us; and thoſe Soldiers that kept Guard over us, would not let us ſleep, but kept ſinging of Songs all night about the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturday</hi> 27. About Nine in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they gave us our breakfaſt, which was the Broath of the Meat they boiled this morning. After our Drivers had bought them all new Whips to drive us along, we began our March, Marching through Two Companies of Soldiers who made a Lane for us, and beat the Drum; we Marched about Nine Miles, until we came to a lone Houſe, where was a Well un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Hedge, by the which we ſat down and eat our Dinner, which was but very ſmall; that done, away we Marched Nine Miles farther, to a Town called <hi>Polonia.</hi> When we came near any Town, then our Drivers would begin to ſmack their Whips, and upon the leaſt occaſion in the World, whip us too, if we did not keep in even Ranks to very great exactneſs; ſo that Laſhes was dealt amongſt us very plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96857:5"/>inſomuch that one of them which took great delight in this Exerciſe of Whipping, we nicknamed <hi>Whipping Tom.</hi> When we came into the Village of <hi>Polonia,</hi> the people appear'd very few, ſo that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately the Town was alarm'd by Ringing of the Church-Bells, according to the manner of an Alarm; then ſoon, into the place where we were, came all the people which lived within the noiſe of the Bells; but truly Nine parts in Ten of the people that we ſaw, was of the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male Sex, and Children. Inever ſaw a Country ſo thin of Men before, which was contrary to what I did expect; for it was uſual in <hi>England,</hi> to hear people ſpeak much of the popularity of <hi>France.</hi> When they had ſerved us our Supper, which was a piece of Black Bread and Water, they put us, ſome into a Stable, and the reſt into an empty Houſe, where we lay on the Brick-Floor, the Country-people being all in Arms to Guard us, both within doors and without.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sunday,</hi> 28. Early in the morning, we were carried out of our Lodgings into the ſtreets, where we all ſate down on the ground, Ten and Ten together, for ſuch were our Meſſes. Now they ſerved us our Breakfaſt and Dinner together, which was Broth cut pretty thick with black courſe Bread, which was ſo four, that the major part of our Men thought they had put Vinegar into it, until by the taſte of the Bread by it ſelf, it was diſcerned: The Meat, that little there was, they alſo gave us, which was not conſiderable; our Drink was Water. When we had thus eaten, away we marched nine miles, to a Town called <hi>Beant:</hi> Juſt as we came into this Town, the People were all go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Maſs, ſo that we had a full ſight of the major part of the people of this place; which were but few, in reſpect to the largeneſs of the Town; and of thoſe, the moſt were Women and Prieſts. Here our Guards made us ſit down all on a row in the middle of the ſtreets, and ſo they commanded the Country-people with their Pails and Buckets to fetch us Water to drink. After we had all drank, away we marched nine miles farther, to a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket-Town called <hi>Dervalle:</hi> When we came into this Town, we were ranged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the ſtreet for the people to behold us; which were not many, and of them the major part were Women and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. After this was over, that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple began to return to their Houſes, being ſatisfied with the fight of ſo many <hi>Engliſh,</hi> which I preſume to think, they never ſaw before, they put us into two Stables, and there ſerved us a Supper, a piece of brown, or rather black Bread, and a Cup of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for each Man. This black Bread was not given to us for the want of any bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be had; for this Country abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with plenty of good Corn; ſuch as Wheat, Rye, Barley, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but becauſe they would not go to the Price of it, although it was very cheap. When we had ſupp'd, we went to ſleep on the Horſe-dung, not having ſo much as a little Litter to cover it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monday,</hi> 29. Early in the morning, we were ready to march, each Man getting a Cup of Water, but that was all; ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way we marched ſeven miles, to a large Town called <hi>Neſce.</hi> Now becauſe there was not a Town upon the Road within leſs than twenty miles, we continued here all day in an Inn, whoſe Yard and Stables did contain us all: They gave us here for our Dinner about an Ounce of Meat <hi>per</hi> Man, with the Pottage it was boil'd in; and at night they gave each Man a piece
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96857:6"/>of brown Bread: Water was brought in to us in a great Kettle, ſo that we had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough of that, and that was all our Drink. At night, we were put up cloſe into Stables,
<note place="margin">Weather fair.</note> and were guarded by the Country-people, who brought their Arms along with them; ſuch as wooden Pitchforks, ſome Hedging-bills, and here and there one of the beſt of them had a Gun; to ſome of them our Guards gave their Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtols and Carbines; but, alas, many of them knew no more what to do with them, than thoſe that never ſaw one in their lives. I ſaw one looking upon his Piſtol, holding the Muzzle in his hand, and with the other hand he was tampering with the Lock: I ſtood looking on him a good while, thinking by and by to ſee the fooliſh Dog ſhoot himſelf; and ſo he had, if he had not been prevented by one of his Brother-Clowns, who came to him, and told him the danger of holding the Piſtol in that manner; and ſo ſhew'd him which end he ſhould hold in his hand: Another of them in the night I ſaw take the Candle, and becauſe it did not burn bright, he was knocking the Candle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Muzzle of his Carbine; which, if Fortune had not certainly favoured Fools, he had without doubt ſhot himſelf. Here our Lodgings were in two Stables, indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent well littered with Straw.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Turſday,</hi> 30. Early in the morning, we marched out of this Town, the weather being fair and clear, we marched twelve miles to a ſingle Houſe, which was an Inn upon the Road. Here we dined; we had here Meat and Pottage a pretty conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable quantity; but no other Drink but Water. When we had dined, we marched eight miles farther, to a ſmall Village called <hi>Treverah.</hi> When we came thither, there was no Lodging to be had for us, nor any thing elſe; ſo here they got ſome of their Country brown Bread, and gave every Man a bit; and alſo they gave a Pot of Wine of about three <hi>Engliſh</hi> Pints, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ten Men; ſo we were all forced to lie down on the cold ground in this open Field, having nothing over head, ſaving the Heavens only, whoſe Spangled Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs entertain'd our eyes for the moſt part of the night. Here they alſo alarm'd this place, that all the Country Boors came in with their Pitchforks and Bills to guard us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wedneſday</hi> 31. By the riſing of the Sun we began to March towards <hi>Nants;</hi> which was diſtant ten Miles; when we begun to come near the Town of <hi>Nants,</hi> they began to exerciſe their Whips upon every looſe occaſion; he that chanced but to ſtir out of the Ranks, was ſure to be laſhed, if any of the Guards were near them; ſo that with their continual Whipping, they had whipt all their new Whips to pieces, that they bought at <hi>Reens,</hi> and ſo here they bought more new Whips. When we had paſt through great part of the Town, we were brought to an Inn, in the which place we were kept backwards in the Yards; here they gave us each Man a penny Loaf of good white Bread; and as for Water, it was brought in by a Horſe in Burreco's, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Water in the Inn was not fit to drink. Here many People came to ſee us, but none were admitted, except they were known to be ſuch as was like their Grand Maſter. It happened that there was a Gentleman came into this Inn to drink, which went up into an upper Room on purpoſe to ſpeak to us out of the window; but as ſoon as he was heard to ſpeak Engliſh, he was immediately
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96857:6"/>hurried out of the Houſe, and withal threatned to be put in priſon: our Dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers had for a long time promiſed to us, That as ſoon as we came for <hi>Nants,</hi> they would give us a Hogſhead of Wine, but inſtead of giving a Hogſhead, they ſtop the Money that a Gentleman gave us, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to buy a Hogſhead, and then they gave a grand pot of ſad ſorry Wine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt ten men, which was not above each man a glaſs; towards night they went into the Market, and bought up a great great deal of the Refuge Fleſh in the Market; ſuch as Sheepſheads, Bullocks Livers and Lights, and the like; ſo that for our Supper we had about an ounce and 2/1 <hi>per</hi> man, with the Pottage this ſtuff was boil'd in; our want made any thing to go down with a pleaſant taſte; our lodging was in the Stables.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thurſday, Aug.</hi> 1. We remained ſtill in this place, our Guards had determined to ſtay all this day to give us a day of reſt: In the morning they gave us each man a ſouſe Loaf, and at night juſt ſuch a Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per as we had laſt night of ſuch Fleſh and Pottage; ſo after Supper we were put up cloſe into the Stables, and a Guard kept at the door.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Friday,</hi> 2. Early in the morning we made ready, being ſoon dreſt, to march, receiving every man a ſouſe Loaf before for breakfaſt and dinner; ſo away we march'd for a Town call'd <hi>Egreville,</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant from <hi>Nants</hi> 12 Mile; as we were upon the Road this day, many of us ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red great drought for want of water, the Road being very duſty, neither did we paſs by any Spring or Wells upon the Road; when we came into the Village call'd <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greville,</hi> we were put into two Stables, and there we were ſerved with Bread; and as for Drink, we had no other than what the Well afforded; after our Supper was end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, we were put up into the Stables to ſleep; this afternoon four of our men had contracted to run away, if any oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity preſented; the which thing they did accompliſh this night.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturday,</hi> 3. About ſix in the morning we were call'd out, and counted, as was their conſtant cuſtome; they miſt four men; then they began to count over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and ſo they did at leaſt ſix times; but when they found that four of our men had deſerted themſelves, you would admire to hear how Jack <hi>French-man</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ſwear, and to abuſe all the reſt. Immediately Horſes and Men were ſent in purſuit ſeveral ways, but none of them could have any intelligence of them; in the mean time we were all carried into a cloſe Barn, and a Guard ſet over us all day: about night our <hi>Guard a Marine</hi> came back, and taking his Roll of our names, call'd us over two by two; and as they came out of the Barn, they were ſorely drubb'd, until ſuch time that he was quite weary, and not able to drub more; withal commanded them to tell where the four men were which had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted themſelves; but alas! no man was able of us to give that account; for, I believe, poor men, they did not know well themſelves where they were. But as for our parts we were all hand-cuft a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain: and becauſe they had loſt ſome of their handcuffs, they bound many of our men with Cords; ſo away we were car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to the place where we lay laſt night, having a great Guard over us all night, giving us nothing but Bread and Water this day.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:96857:7"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sund.</hi> 4. Early in the morning we march'd out of this Town into a ſmall Town, whoſe name I have loſt; in this Town we were conducted to a cloſe yard, where we were ſerved our Dinners, which was brown bread and water; after we din'd, away we march'd to a Town which was diſtant from <hi>Egreville</hi> twelve miles, call'd St. <hi>Saravan:</hi> now the weather being very Rainy, we went no farther than this Town, but lodged all night in a Stable; our ſupper was ſuch as our Dinner, bread and water; ſo here we were well guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all night by the Inhabitants of the place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monday,</hi> 5. Early in the morning we were ſerved with bread and water, ſo away we march'd twenty miles to a Town call'd St. <hi>Vincean,</hi> the Road very good; but by reaſon of the duſtineſs of the Road, and the want of water, we ſuffered great drought; when we came into Town, we were drove into a great Inn, in which was a great ſquare Yard; here they ſerved us our Supper, brown bread and water, but here they gave us each man a ſmall bit of Butter; I am ſure the Pot would not hold ſix pound that ſerved two hundred, the quantity and goodneſs were both alike, for it had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny colours, and very naſty ſtuff; not but that there is good Butter to be had here, and enough. After we had ſupp'd, we went into the Stables to ſleep, where our Lodging was on the dung, having very little or no Litter under us; the Houſe was alſo well guarded by the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tueſday,</hi> 6. Early in the morning we made ready to march, eating our Break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt and Dinner both under one, before we came forth, which was brown Bread and VVater, by the ſtrength of which we were to march Twenty Miles, before we were to eat any more: In this Town, ſeveral of the Towns-people came to me, and very kindly asked me, how I did, and would, if it had been poſſible have perſuaded me, that I was a <hi>French</hi>-man, and born in this Village, and therefore deſir'd me to ſpeak my Native Tongue to them; they did not ſtick to ſwear, that I was born here, unto our Guards. From hence we marched Twenty Miles, to a Village, called St. <hi>Jacque,</hi> when we came into this Town, we ſaw our <hi>Guard a Marine,</hi> who left us at <hi>Egreville,</hi> in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit of the four Men that deſerted. He told us, that he had taken them; and withal told us, that he had beat them ſo long, that he had broke three Sticks over their Backs, which we after knew to be falſe, for he pretended he had ſent them to <hi>Rochefort</hi> before us, which when we came there, we found there was no ſuch Men. In this Town they put us all into an empty Houſe, where our Lodging was on the bare Floor. At our entrance into the Town they rang their Bells to larm the People, who by the quantity that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, would have gave a Man to think, that there had lately been ſome Contagion that had ſwept all, or moſt all away, ſo few did the People appear. Our Supper was here Bread, and each Man a Glaſs of Wine and Water; ſo after Supper was done, we lay down to Sleep, but were prevented by their beating a Drum at the Door all Night; and ſo like to Negroes they beat and made a noiſe, as if they had been the ſame. The chief Man in this place was upon the Guard to Night, and his Accoutrements were ſuch, that for want of a belt for his Sword, he was forc'd to make it faſt to him with a piece
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:96857:7"/>of an old Halter; and this Man, our Guard told me, was the Mayor of the place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wedneſday</hi> 7. About Noon we march'd out of this Town; but before we went out of the Town, we expected we ſhould have ſome Food; ſome of our Men asked the <hi>Guard a Marine,</hi> if he would give us any Food, for he told him our People were not able to March without; he preſently fell to whipping him with his whip, and told them they ſhould have none until Night: So away we march'd twelve Miles to a Village, call'd <hi>Shearone;</hi> we croſs'd over a River juſt by this Town in a Ferry-boat at twice, all of us; and when we came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Town, we were put ſome into a Barn, and the reſt into Stables very well Litter'd; our Supper was here a piece of brown Bread, and about half an Ounce of Butter <hi>per</hi> Man, and our Drink was water: Now we being near the Sea-ſide, they were very fearful we ſhould make our Eſcapes in ſome of their Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toons, which lay in ſight; for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting of which, they got at leaſt 30 Men very well arm'd with Firelocks to guard us all Night.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thurſday,</hi> 8. Early in the Morning we began to march toward <hi>Rochel,</hi> which was diſtant twelve Miles; within ſix Miles of <hi>Rochel,</hi> was a Town in the which they gave us Bread, and ſeveral heads of Garlick, which they heaved into the road amongſt us, to make us ſcramble in the dirt for it: here they took off all our Mens handcuffs, and looſed them, becauſe they ſhould not be ſeen in that manner in the Town of <hi>Rochel.</hi> About three in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon we came into the Town of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel,</hi> where we ſaw many of their Soldiers at work, with other Artificers, in building of Mud-walls, and digging of Moats, and laying out ſeveral Lines of Fortification. As we paſſed by the Soldiers, they left off their work, and came running at us open-mouth'd, calling us what ugly names they could, and withal railing againſt the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> moſt deſperately, until ſuch time that their Officers came and drubb'd them to their work. VVhen we got into the City, we heard many of the people ſpeak good <hi>Engliſh,</hi> giving us their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to God for our Deliverance; and all that could well come near us, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately gave us their Charity. VVhen they brought us to a round Tower next the water-ſide, we ſate down in the Street for the ſpace of half an hour, in the which time the good people of the place brought us a great quantity of pure white Bread, and would have given us many things elſe, but were hindred by thoſe Rogues that guarded us. After the half-hour ſtop, as aforeſaid, we were all put into this round Tower. Our Guards here gave us no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to eat or to drink; but the good people of this place got leave of the Men that belonged to the Town, that guarded us, to come in and relieve us, and ſo they did, for they brought us white Bread and Butter enough, and a ſufficient quantity of good VVine. At night we lay all down to ſleep on the cold Stones.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Friday</hi> 9. About Eight in the Morning we were brought out of this Tower; and as we paſt along the Streets, the People gave us their Charity. Towards the further part of the Town, we were ordered to ſit down in the Street, where we were ſerved our Breakfaſt, <hi>viz,</hi> a ſix <hi>Denire</hi> Loaf, and one <hi>Sirdena per</hi> Man; that done, away we marched towards <hi>Rochefort,</hi> being diſtant Fifteen Miles, ſome
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96857:8"/>call it Twenty one Miles; but by the way, at a ſingle Inn, about half way be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Rochel</hi> and <hi>Rochefort,</hi> we ſat down and were ſerved with Bread and Water; from hence we marched to <hi>Rochefort;</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Seven in the Evening we entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Town, and ſo were carried to the Priſon; there we found about 200 of <hi>Dutch</hi>-Men, which were ſeized upon, and ſtopt at <hi>Bourdeaux.</hi> This Priſon of <hi>Rochefort,</hi> is, I believe, as fine a Priſon as any is in <hi>Europe,</hi> for without doubt, it was not deſigned for a Priſon, for the Rooms were very neatly laid out with very fine Chimneys, and curious Glaſs Laſh-lights. It is ſaid, thoſe Houſes were built for the King's Officers to live in; within the Gates of the Priſon was a large Square Court, which did not contain leſs than 140 Square Perches, and all over-grown with Graſs. In this place, when we came in, we ſat down on the ground, and to every Seven Men we had a Loaf given, and a Can of pretty good Wine; after we had Eat and Drank, we went into the Priſon, where we lay on the Floor. The <hi>Dutch</hi>-men that were there before, had Beds to lye on in very good order; neither were they bare of Cloaths, as we were, by reaſon they had liberty to ſave both Cloaths and Money, being only ſtopt and ſeized in the River of <hi>Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaux</hi> and <hi>Sherant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturday,</hi> 10. About Ten in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Clerk came in, and took our Names, with the Ships Names we were taken in; after which, we Meſt our ſelves ſeven and ſeven together. Four days in the week they gave us Meat, but it was but very little; and at night Beans: The other three days we had Fiſh; but the quantity did not exceed an Ounce <hi>per</hi> Man; and thoſe nights we had Peaſe. Three times a day we were ſerved Wine about half a Pint <hi>per</hi> Man for a Meal, and the VVine not much to be found fault with. As for Bread, we had about ſix Pound <hi>per</hi> day for ſeven Men. Every thing now was ten times better than it was when we came from <hi>Thoulon.</hi> Our Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was on the Floor for the moſt part of us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturday,</hi> 17. Very near 200 more <hi>Engliſh</hi>-men were brought hither from <hi>Breſt,</hi> who came all the way in Irons: They told us, they far'd very well upon the Road, in reſpect to us. About thirty came alſo from <hi>Port-Lewis,</hi> preſently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Amongſt thoſe that came from <hi>Breſt,</hi> were two of thoſe Men that deſerted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from us at <hi>Egreville.</hi> They told me, They had been down at <hi>Penbeef,</hi> and there lay a <hi>Dane;</hi> they got on board of him; but the <hi>Dane</hi> was ſo unkind to them, he would not carry them out, but put them aſhoar again, and would not entertain them; and as they were wandring up and down, they knew not which way, they chanc'd to croſs the Road juſt as theſe Men were paſſing by, who came from <hi>Breſt:</hi> now becauſe this Provoſt had loſt ſome of his Men upon the Road, he ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeth theſe two Lads, and put them in Irons, and brought them hither.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Friday,</hi> 23. About Noon, this day of <hi>Engliſh, Scots, Sweeds,</hi> and <hi>Danes,</hi> were muſtered to the number of 200. and were drawn out of the Priſon into a Cloſe, oppoſite to the Priſon, by twenty Couple together; when we came there, there was a ſtrong Guard of Soldiers, and with them ſeveral Smiths, having all things for their purpoſe in readineſs; ſo we were forthwith all put into Irons, Handcuff'd two and two together; and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:96857:8"/>after this was done, to make us the more ſecure to them, they made twenty Couple of us faſt together, by ranging a Rope, and faſtning it to each pair of Handcuffs, giving us about three Foot ſpace, juſt to tread clear of one anothers Heels. In this order we were all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to ſit down in Rank on the Ground; that done, they gave Shoes to all ſuch as wanted to perform this long Journey; after this they gave us our Dinners, Bread and Sirdena's, with a Cup of ſowr Beverage; our Dinner be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ended, we began our march, croſſing the River of <hi>Sherant</hi> in the Ferry-boats; ſo away we march to a Town three Leagues diſtant, call'd St. <hi>Jan Englae,</hi> on the outſide of which Town was an old Caſtle, and a great Farm adjacent; in this Cloſe we were all rang'd in rank on the ground; ſo they ſerved us our Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which was one Egg and one Sirdena for a Man, with a Cup of Beverage VVine; that done, we were all put into a Stable or Barn, wherein was plenty of Straw, where we got a very good nights Reſt, the beſt I ever got in <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturday,</hi> 24. Early this morning, we were rouzed to march, being ſoon dreſt: ſo being roped together, and counted, we marched three Leagues, without eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or drinking, to a Town called <hi>Ogua:</hi> In this Town they drew us all together into a place which formerly was a Bury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing place for Proteſtants; here they gave us our Dinner, which was a Diſh of Broth, as they call it; but it was ſuch, that the like I never taſted for naſtineſs, having no Meat boil'd in it: I do ſuppoſe they threw into it a little naſty Oyl, and ſo, with ſome brown Bread put into it, they gave us this ſtuff for our Dinner; but this ſtuff fell ſhort, that it would not ſerve all the Men; ſo they afterward gave amongſt us about thirty Eggs; ſo with this, and a Cup of ſmall Beverage, we made our Dinner: After Dinner, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way we marched to a ſmall Town at the Mouth of the River of <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> called <hi>Raan.</hi> Entring this Town, they made us all ſit down on the Sand by the Sea-ſide, becauſe that none of the Inhabitants of the Town ſhould come near us; in which place we ſate until ſuch time as they had provided us a Lodging-place; keeping, in the mean time, ſtrict Guard over us, to hinder the Towns-people from giving us any thing; ſo that they could only ſtand at a diſtance, bemoaning our ſad condition with ſhowrs of tears, but durſt not come near us, for fear of the Guards. The people of this Town, and likewiſe of the Town of St. <hi>Jan Angliae,</hi> are known to be the major part of them Proteſtants. We ſate ſo long on the Sand, before they had provided us Lodging, that the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Tide had driven us up to the very doors; after which, we were driven into an empty Houſe, in which we lay all night, not ſuffering one man to go out to eaſe himſelf, ſo that thoſe that had occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, were forc'd to do it where we lay. They gave us for our Supper an Egg, and one ſmall Sirdena, with a piece of Bread, and a Cup of Beverage for each Man, ſo here we ſlept, though moſt ſadly annoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the ill ſcent of our own Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sunday,</hi> 25. We remained in this Town until Two in the Afternoon, and had our Dinner here, which was one Egg and one Sirdena, with a piece of Bread and a Cup of Beverage <hi>per</hi> Man. All this morning was not one Man admitted to go out to eaſe himſelf; in which ſad manner we continued, until the two Barques were
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:96857:9"/>ready to take us in. At Two in the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon we came all forth; and as we came out, we were ſtrictly ſearched for Knives or Razors, notwithſtanding our being ſo ſtrictly ſearched at <hi>Rochfort:</hi> that done, we were all made faſt together in two parcels, an hundred Men in each par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, for all we had no further to march than about a Bowe-ſhot: but ſuch was their great fear of our being reſcu'd by theſe Proteſtant People, or at leaſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veying us away from them. Many of the people of the Town followed us at a diſtance, heaving after us Apples, Pears, and Plums, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We walked down almoſt as low as Low-water-mark, where we entred into two ſmall Barks, call'd <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toons,</hi> alias <hi>Brittoons.</hi> When, and as faſt as we came aboard, we were an hundred of us forced down into her ſmall Hold, ſtowing one upon the other in a moſt miſerable condition; ſo that neither with Tongue nor Pen am I able to expreſs the miſery we endured while we were on board the Barque, both for want of Air and Room; and many times were the Hatches all laid cloſe over us for ſome time, until we that were next to them were forced to heave them open, for fear of ſtiffing all the reſt of the Men. At the firſt of the floud, we floated, and away up the River we went, having in our Company the <hi>Pottaſh,</hi> or Guard-ſhip of that place, to be our Guard. At night they gave us one Egg, and one Sirdena, with a ſmall bit of Bread and a cup of Water <hi>per</hi> Man; ſo here we remained in a moſt miſerable condition, not having room to ſit, ſtand, or lie down.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monday,</hi> 26. We continu'd ſtill on board the Barques, anchoring every Tide of Ebb, the Wind being Eaſterly, ſo upon the Flood turned it up the River. Our whole days allowance to day was a ſmall bit of Bread, with one Egg, and one Sir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dena, and a cup of Water <hi>per</hi> Man, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing ſtill on board the Barque, in a moſt miſerable condition.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tueſday,</hi> 27. About Noon this day we got up as high as <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> anchoring oppoſite to the Town. As ſoon as the News of our being there was got aſhore, off came the People of all ſorts and ſizes, both gentle and ſimple, and beſides a very great number ſtood on the Shore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide. Thoſe that came off to us were not ſuffered to come near us; yet ſome of our people did get ſome relief by ſtealth, and did privately convey ſome Letters aſhore. About Four in the Afternoon, they gave us each Man a Bisket-Cake, and two Sirdena's, and a cup of VVine. Supper being done, ſeveral of our Men were put into a great flat Boat, to give more room for the reſt: but their Lodging was this night very bad, for about Nine at night it began to thunder, lighten, and rain, as if Heaven and Earth would have met; in the mean time, our poor people lay in an open Boat, having no ſhelter at all; nor in the morning any dry Cloaths to ſhift themſelves; but if they had, they could make no ſhift, by reaſon of their Irons; which would not admit of any ſuch thing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> 28. About Eight this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning we were all put into two flat Boats, in order to our paſſage up the River: in theſe Boats alſo we were ſtow'd very cloſe, but yet not half ſo cloſe as before. Ere we looſned from before the Town, off came an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchant, who got per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to ſhare amongſt us ſome Money which he had collected for us amongſt the reſt of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants: He
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96857:9"/>gave amongſt us very near Twelve Pound <hi>ſterling,</hi> and alſo ſeveral <hi>French</hi> Merchants gave us Loaves of Bread, and Jars of VVine and Brandy, and ſeveral roaſted Geeſe; all of them wiſhing us well. Our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants promiſed us. That they would write to <hi>England,</hi> and give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of us. About ¾ Flood, we looſed, and away we went, until the Tide was done; then we came to an Anchor oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to a ſingle Houſe on the North-ſide of the River, where we ſtaid until the Ebb was done. Our Supper was two Sirdena's <hi>per</hi> Man, with Bread and Beve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage; ſo the firſt of the Flood away we went, Sail and Oars.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thurſday,</hi> 29. About Noon this day we were tract up as high as the Town of <hi>Langoon;</hi> a little higher on the North ſide was a ſmall Village, oppoſite to which we Din'd; our Dinner was one Egg, and one <hi>Siderna per</hi> Man, with Bread and Beverage, as at other times; at night we came to a ſmall Town on the North-ſide of the River, called <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dero,</hi> here we went aſhore all of us, and lay all Night in an empty Houſe, our Supper was Mutton and Broth; but as for the Mutton, the quantity was ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream ſmall, that one Man might with eaſe eat Twenty Mens allowance; with about Two Gallons of Beverage for Twenty Men: many that had no Veſſels, ſuch as Drinking-Pots, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were forced to put their Broath or Wine into their Hats: In this ſavage manner were we often ſerved by theſe Bruitiſh <hi>French</hi>-men. Supper being ended, we went all to ſleep on the bare floor, the Houſe being well guarded round, both within and without.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Friday</hi> 30. Early in the Morning we came down to the Boats, being flouted and ſcoffed at by the people all the way we we paſſed, calling us Rebellious Rogues for Fighting againſt our lawful King <hi>James;</hi> one who, as they ſay, was as righteous as a God; and withal run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning out ſtrangely againſt King <hi>William,</hi> calling him <hi>Jack Orange,</hi> and ſaying, they would cut his Throat in a ſhort time, and make us all Gally-ſlaves; yet for all this, we paſt along, taking no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther notice of them than this, by laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at their fooliſhneſs: We entred all into the Boats, and away we went; about Noon they gave to each Man of us for Dinner one <hi>Sirdena,</hi> and one Head of <hi>Garlick,</hi> with Bread and Beverage; and for Supper, one Egg and one <hi>Sirdena,</hi> with Bread and Beverage: So we ſlept all Night in the open Boats, having no Canopy but the Heavens, the Weather fair and clear.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturday</hi> 31. In the Morning very early, the Boat-men began to work, tracking us up the River; ſometimes we had at leaſt Thirty to a Boat; about Noon we came oppoſite to a great Town on the North-ſide of the River, called <hi>Marmanda,</hi> and went all aſhore, where our Guards, upon ſome ſuſpicion, ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all our Irons, ſome they found had broke their Forelocks, to them they gave a ſufficient quantity of drubs with a great ſtick; ſo immediately a Smith was ſent for to ſecure them, and make them faſter: That done, we were ordered into the Boats again, where they gave us our Dinner, one Egg and one <hi>Sirdena,</hi> with Bread and Beverage; and for Supper the like. We came to an Anchor cloſe by the Shore, near no Town, where we
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96857:10"/>lay all Night in the open Boats, having nothing to cover us: our Bodies being watered with ſeveral great ſhowers of Rain.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>September, Sunday,</hi> 1. In the Morning early we began to put forward, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Noon we came oppoſite to a Town on the North-ſide of the River, called <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port;</hi> this day they pretended we ſhould make a very great Feaſt of Fleſh; ſo at, or about Noon they gave us about an Ounce of Fat <hi>Pork;</hi> for it is the faſhion of this Country to cut away all the Lean clean off the <hi>Pork,</hi> and then eat the Fat after it is Salted. They ſtop'd us about half an hour before the Town, on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to make a ſhow of us to the People, the major part of them ſtanding laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at us, as if ſuch fooliſh Slaves as they are, were not ſubject to the fortune of War as well as we: Then we went up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards until night, when they always came to an Anchor, by reaſon that there is no Tracking in the Night, for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Shoals and Iſlands there is in the River. At Night they gave us for Supper one Egg and one <hi>Sirdena per</hi> Man; ſo we lay all night in the open Boats, the Weather fair and clear.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monday</hi> 2. This day we paſt by ſeveral ſmall Towns on both ſides of the River, whoſe names are inſignificant; the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of one of them, when we put aſhore, brought us down into the Boats to ſell, ſeveral Roaſted Geeſe; thoſe that had Money amongſt us, bought of them very cheap, a good Roaſted Gooſe, not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celling the price of Six Souſe; our Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians gave us for Dinner one Egg and one <hi>Sirdena,</hi> with Bread and Beverage, and the like for Supper; ſo we lay ſtill in the open Boats all Night.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tueſday</hi> 3. We continued ſtill on Board the Boats, not going by Night aſhore; our poor bodies lay open to the Dew of Heaven, it Rained on us ſeveral great ſhowers of Rain this Night. By this time we had about Twenty four Men ſick, ſome of one Malady, and ſome of an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; our Diet was to day our former al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance of Eggs, and <hi>Sirdena</hi>'s, and Bread, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wedneſday</hi> 4. We continued ſtill on Board the Boats in this ſad condition; our Diet to day was about an Ounce of naſty greaſy <hi>Pork;</hi> and for thoſe that were ſick, that could not eat it, they muſt faſt; for there was nothing elſe to be given to them, although all manner of things fitting for the body of Man, for food, was extream cheap all over this Country; this we had for Dinner and for Supper. At Night we came up to a Town on the South-ſide of the River, called St. <hi>Anns,</hi> here we Anchored very near the Shore, about Eight at Night it began to Thunder, and Lighten, and Rain, as if Heaven and Earth would have met; we got a thin Sail to heave over the after-part of the Boat; but that did us but little ſervice, it not being proof againſt Water, we were all deſperate wet: The people of the Town kept a ſtrong Guard all Night on the Shore. About Eleven this Night died one of our ſick Men, named <hi>Thomas Smith,</hi> who was lately, Mate of a <hi>Virginia</hi> Ship, he was put in Irons to one of his Sons, who when his Father was dead, vvas yet kept in Irons faſt to his dead Father, for the ſpace of Eight hours; the ſight of vvhich vvas able to melt a heart of ſtone to ſee a poor Youth vveeping and lamenting the loſs of his Father, and at the ſame time to be Chained to him.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:96857:10"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thurſday,</hi> 5. About Eight this Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they carried aſhore the body of the Dead man, by Four men; but like them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves they carried him, one taking hold of a leg, another of an arm, and ſo dog-like, heaved him into a hole by the way-ſide: They gave us our Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner here before we came from before this Town, which was about an Ounce of ruſty Pork with Bread and Beverage, and the ſame for Supper: By Night we came to a Town on the <hi>South</hi>-ſide of the River call'd <hi>Ratta,</hi> at which Town we went aſhore, where we lay all night in a Barn, having a great Guard over us all night, quite round the Houſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Friday,</hi> 6. While we lay in this Barn, ſick and well all together, we were moſt ſadly annoyed by the ill ſcents of our mens Excrements; for they were not admitted to go forth to eaſe themſelves, the Inhumanity of the Guards was ſuch; much like to the reſt of their Countrey-men, who are, by all that I can diſcern of them in general, the moſt inhumane, barbarous Wretches, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver lived ſince the Creation. In the Morning one of our Boys ſpied a hole in the Wall of the Barn, that look'd into another Barn, in which was a Wine-preſs, and abundance of Grapes ready for the Preſs; one of our boys crept in at the hole, and handed out to the moſt part of our men their hats full of Grapes, which was a great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing to us, beſides filling our empty ſtomachs. About Nine in the morning we came out of this Barn; and as we were marching down towards the Boats, ſeveral of our ſick men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained to the Provo of their extream illneſs; he preſently told them in <hi>French,</hi> That they muſt pray to God for for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs, for from him they muſt not expect any Mercy or Comfort. At Dinner they gave us one <hi>Sirdena,</hi> and one Onion betwixt two men; and for Supper juſt the ſame. At night we were brought up oppoſite to a Town call'd <hi>Burdoon,</hi> on the <hi>South</hi> ſide of the River; cloſe by the Shore ſide, we were brought to an Anchor: When the rumour of being there was ſpread abroad about the Town, both Gentle and Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple came down to ſtare on us, and ſo ſpend their Verdict, and ſo away again. All this night we lay in the Boat, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a great Guard over us all Night on the Shore ſide.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturday,</hi> 7. Before it was day, we weighed from before the Town, the morning being foggy, and the day ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hot; as ſoon as it began to clear up, we ſaw the high <hi>Granada</hi> Hills very plain, the middle of them bearing <hi>South</hi> from us. Our Dinner was one <hi>Sirdena per</hi> man, and one <hi>Onion</hi> betwixt two men, with Bread and Beverage. About two in the Afternoon we came to a Shoal place in the River, where we were all forc'd to get out of the Boat to lighten her. So we walk'd about a mile, at the end of which the Boat put aſhore, and thoſe that were able to walk a mile, came out of the boat; that done, we took up that little baggage we had, and away we march'd, leaving our ſick men on the ſhore, until ſuch time as they could get Carts to carry them. About a mile from the place where we landed, was a Town call'd <hi>Grana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da:</hi> cloſe by the Gates of the Town we ſat down until the ſick men were brought to us. We ſat there at leaſt
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:96857:11"/>two hours before the Carts came; in the mean time ſome of us joined our ſtocks together, and ſent into the Town for ſome Wine by a Soldier, that was as a Spectator, looking upon us; he took ſeveral of our Jars, and brought them full of Wine, and the reſt of our Money back, when we our ſelves did not expect that our Money would have bought a quarter ſo much; but Wine was ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary cheap, that by Retail it was ſold for leſs than three half-pence <hi>per</hi> Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, that is, eight <hi>deniers</hi> the grand Pot; and the Wine was alſo very good; when our ſick men came to us, we all entred the Gates of the Town, and were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted to the Market-houſe, and by it was an empty houſe, where they uſed to put dry Goods, as Wheat, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> into this houſe we were all for cloſe cramm'd, that we had ſcarcely room to ſtand one by the other; here many of our men got their loads of the Juice of the Grapes, inſomuch that they fell to fighting one with the other; the Guards coming in to part them, began to ſtrike ſeveral of them, but they immediately left off fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one with the other, and fell foul on the Guards, but alas! they came off by the worſt, being all hand-cufft two and two together. At night they brought us our Supper, Bread and Onions, with ſome few Eggs and Sirdena's, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of ſerving us, they pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed us, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving both the Eggs, and Sirdena's, and Onions at us, with all their force; I had a blow juſt on my belly with a great Onion, that truly I thought it had beat all the breath out of my body, and the Eggs were moſt of them broke all to pieces, the reſt were thrown on the ground in the middle of the houſe, juſt as if they were ſerving ſo many Hogs. Before we went to ſleep, they took many of the ſick men out of the houſe, and put them into another, to make a little more room for the reſt to lye down: That being done, we went to ſleep, but were moſt ſadly annoyed before morning, with the ſad ſtink of our mens excrements; the Towns Guard being ſo like themſelves, they would not ſuffer any man to go forth to eaſe himſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sunday,</hi> 8. After our Guards had been at Maſs, we came forth out of this place, and ſo with two Ropes they made us faſt together, about Eighty men or thereabout, in a Rope; for ſome of the ſick they had provided two Carts, but two Carts was not ſufficient to carry all of them; the reſt they made faſt to us in the Ropes, on purpoſe that if they could not march, we might drag them along, which we were forc'd to do by their continual drubbing us with Whips, Swords, Sticks, and with their Guns likewiſe, if we did but ſtop to the cries of our ſick men; juſt as I have ſeen Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in <hi>England</hi> do to their Horſes when they were upon a dead pull, giving each one a lick to mend his pace; ſo did the barbarous <hi>Frenchmen</hi> to us; many times the ſick fell down on the ground, not being able to ſtand; then were theſe poor ſouls dragg'd along on the ground by one arm, with a <hi>Frenchman</hi> following them, drubbing them, crying, March ye bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering Dogs, and ſo never leave drub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing, until he had made them to ſtand; and if by no means they could, then they would uſe them after this manner; They would take them out of the rope, and ſo heave them into the Carts, like ſo many dead Dogs one upon the other; ſo that I think it would melt a heart of ſtone to behold it. I ſaw one of theſe Rogues drub a poor man that had the Calenture,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:96857:11"/>and was at the ſame time as ſenſeleſs as a Stone, moſt deſperately, to cauſe him to make more room in the Cart; and alas, the poor Man he cried at his Blows, but did not conceive what the occaſion of them was; the next day the Man died of his Diſtemper; in this manner we marched two Leagues, and the end of which, we came to a ſingle Inn by the Road-ſide; here we ſat down to eat our Dinner and Break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt, which was always given us at one time, and now it was a piece of Bread, and one Egg <hi>per</hi> Man, with a Glaſs of VVine; Dinner be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ended,
<note place="margin">Tholuſe, Languedo.</note> away we marched three Leagues further to the great City of <hi>Tholuſe;</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Eight at Night we came cloſe to the Gates of the City, where thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of People of all ſorts and ſizes came out to ſee ſo many <hi>Engliſh</hi>-men as we were in that Condition, but none was ſuffered to come near us, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept by ſtealth; on the out-ſide of the City we were all drove into to a cold, wet Stable, Sick and VVell all together; where we had neither bit of Bread, nor drop of Drink given us; neither would they let thoſe that had any Money buy any; the place was guard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all round by the Inhabitants of the place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monday,</hi> 9. This Morning about Ten of the Clock, we were all brought out of the Stable, and as we were counted, ſo we were ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped together; we were then order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſit down on the Ground in the Cloſe, juſt without the Stable; and here, to make us amends for our Supper, they gave us this great Dinner, <hi>viz.</hi> about an Ounce of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, ruſty, greaſy Pork, ſuch it was, that many of our hungry Stomacks could not away with; but withal, we had a ſouſe Loaf, and a Cup of Wine and Water <hi>per</hi> Man; Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner being thus ended, we remained in this place to be made a ſhow of to the People; the end for which we travelled about the Country; for the People of the place gave Money to come in to ſee us, and the Rogues the Guard told them, that we were a Man of Wars Mens Company, whom they had taken; alſo alledging us to be a pack of Rebellious Rogues, that had fought againſt Righteous King <hi>James,</hi> and that by the King of <hi>France</hi> we were condemned to be made Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-ſlaves of, and moſt of the common ſort of People believed it, but the better Sort of People were more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitive into the truth of the matter; this we underſtood by ſome of our People that ſpoke <hi>French</hi> very well; who told them, that as yet, they had not as we could hear, gained that point of Honour as to take an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Man of War;
<note place="margin">Five of our Men was left here in their Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal.</note> but otherwiſe we were of us at leaſt thirty Ships Companies of Merchants Ships Men, and moſt of them Ships of no force at all; ſeveral of the Gentry ſeem'd to pity us; but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Information, that we were not of their Opinion, but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, that we were <hi>Calviniſts;</hi> their Charity to us was barefooted and cold; while we lay in this place, I do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:96857:12"/>there was not leſs than Twenty ſeveral Orders of Clergy-men came in to ſee us, telling us we were wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed People, for fighting againſt God and the True Religion; withal, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling us, That their Beads which they ſhew'd to us, and their Prayers in their Cloyſter, was of greater force than our Arms of <hi>England;</hi> they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of us, if there were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us any <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks? we told them, none of the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> but we had one <hi>Iriſh</hi>-man that was, which was a poor ſilly Soul, that ſcarcely knew Good from Evil; we brought them to him; and when they came to him, he underſtood not one word they ſpake; they croſt him, and that the <hi>French</hi> had done before by taking him; and bleſt him, and that was but ſmall benefit to him; ſo away they went; the poor Soul kiſt their Sleeves at their departure, to ſhew his Obedience to their Church. About Two in the Afternoon, we marched from hence; the People flock'd to ſee us in a great number, both Gentry and others: For this City is as near as I can gueſs, who was born in <hi>London,</hi> to be very near, if not quite as big as the City of <hi>London</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Walls; and beſides, the City is very populous, the City is wall'd round with a Brick-wall, with a Trench or Ditch without the Wall, but that was filled up, and Gardens made in the ſame; there is little or no Suburbs belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this City, except it be here and there a ſtragling Houſe; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Town-walls, I could not ſee one piece of Ordnance, nor any For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification; and I am ſure we walkt the Wall three quarters of it Circuit; we had not marched above a quarter of a Mile, but we ſaw two Men that was broke on the VVheel not long ſince; as far as I could gather, it was for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Hugonots</hi> or <hi>Calviniſts;</hi> and we had ſeveral Men with us that ſpoke <hi>French</hi> naturally; we marched two Leagues further, to a Town call <hi>Caſtinata;</hi> when we came there, we were made to ſit down on the cold Ground, until they had ſerved us our Supper, which was a half-peny Loaf, and a Cup of VVine; that being done, we were put into a Stable, and lay on hot Horſe-dung, like ſo many Swine, the Town being all in Arms to guard us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tueſday,</hi> 10. Early in the Morning we were counted like ſo many Sheep, and we were roped together, and away we marched three Leagues to a Town called <hi>Baſiego,</hi> juſt about Twelve of the Clock we entred the Town; juſt at our Entrance, we met a great Concouſe of People attending a Funeral, which was ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnized after this manner: I taking eſpecial notice thereof in all its Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, which was thus: The Prieſt walking before the Corps reading the Service, which was carried on a Bier very neatly dreſt, and before him was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried a wooden Crucifix, the Prieſt was dreſt up in his Pontifical Habit, and after him came one carrying Holy VVater, ſprinkling the People as he paſt; but that which made me almoſt ready to Laugh, was to ſee a VVoman that came after, aſſiſting
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:96857:12"/>the Ceremony with two Tallow Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles burning in one hand, and her Apron held before the Candles with the other, to keep the VVind from blowing them out, the Tallow of the Candles running about her fiſt, the Sun at the ſame time ſhining very reſplendently: The Ceremony was no ſooner done, but in comes the Prieſt into the Town, and pulls off the old Trumpery of the Pope, and got amongſt the Crowd ſtaring on us, and by his Countenance was very well pleaſed at the ſight, to ſee ſo many <hi>Engliſh</hi>-men in Irons, and Roped to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ſitting on the Ground in the middle of the Street, eating an Egg, and one Onion, with Bread and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verage for their Dinner; by this time they had followed their drubbing us ſo cloſe, that they had broke all their Sticks, and moſt of their Swords, and the Barrel of one of their Guns about our Backs: we have now about thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of our Men very Sick in the Carts, who never miſt of drubbing ſcarcely two hours in the day; ſome becauſe of their weakneſs, they were not able to get up into the Carts; and ſome for ſtirring in the Carts, ſometimes to get a little eaſe; we marched two Leagues further to a Town, called <hi>Villa Franko,</hi> where we ſat down in the middle of the Streets, and got our Suppers, one Egg <hi>per</hi> Man, and one Onion betwixt two Men; when our Supper was end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, we were drove into a Stable, where our Lodging was on the hot Horſe-dung, the Houſe being guard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all round by the People of the Town.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> 11. Very early in the Morning we were brought forth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing roped together, and counted like Sheep, the Sick put into the Carts, who never miſt of drubs, for that they had duly paid, and that very often in a day; away we marched three Leagues to a large Town, called <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtela;</hi> when we came into the Town, we ſat down in the Streets in three Ranks; here they gave us for Dinner, three ſmall Sirdena's <hi>per</hi> Man, with Bread and Beverage; ſeveral of our People would have bought ſomething elſe of the People, but durſt not, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it were by Stealth; there was one of our Men went to buy of a poor Woman, a little plate of fry'd Meat, which was diſcovered by the Rogues the Guards, who took away the Meat from the Woman by force, and hove away the Meat, Plate, and all into the middle of the Streets, broke the Plate, and ſpoil'd all the Meat, and this was their Cruelty, who would not give us Victuals ſcarcely enough to keep Life and Soul together; neither would they ſuffer thoſe that had Money to buy any, except it were by ſtealth: we marched from hence three Leagues to a Town, called <hi>Villa Picta,</hi> it was Eight at Night before we entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Town, we being moſt of us moſt deſperately tired with this days Walk, which was ſix Leagues, and every League in <hi>Languedock,</hi> contains four <hi>Italian</hi> Miles; when we came into the Town, we were all put into a great Stable, our Supper was one Sirdena <hi>per</hi> Man, with Bread and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verage; our Lodging was on the hot
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:96857:13"/>Horſe-dung, ſo in this manner we reſted our weary Bones: This Afternoon we ſaw the Highland of <hi>Barcelona</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> very plain.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thurſday,</hi> 12. Early in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we began our march, and marched three Leagues to a Town called <hi>Villa Sancta,</hi> in which place we ſat down in the middle of the ſtreets in ranks; here they ſerved for Dinner, a ſmall bit of bread, with one Egg, and a cup of ſad Beverage Wine, a very poor Dinner. Our ſick men were this day, as well as others, ſorely drubb'd with Swords, Whips, and Sticks, becauſe by their weakneſs many of them were not able to help themſelves up and down; from hence we marched three leagues farther, to a Town call'd <hi>Carkaſonna;</hi> when we came there, the Inhabitants of the Town ſhut the Gates againſt us, and would not let us enter until ſuch time as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voſt, who was our Grand Signior, made uſe of his utmoſt Authority, by ſhewing his Commiſſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Then the Gates were opened, and in we all entred, where we were conduct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a very large ſtable, in which we were all put, ſick and well. Our Supper was a bit of fat Pork, about the bigneſs of a Wallnut, and bread to the quantity of a ſouce loaf, and each man a cup of Beverage. Our lodging was on the hot horſe-dung, which was as hot as any horſe-dung whatſoever. This Town of <hi>Carkaſonna</hi> is a very fine fenced Town, with good Fortifications about it, yet in all the Fortifications I could not ſee any Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, mounted or unmounted: The Town ſeemed to be very populous, but at this time there were no men in Arms in this Town, ſuch as Soldiers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Friday,</hi> 13. Before we came out of this Stable, they ſerved us our Dinner, which was a ſmall bit of Pork, like that laſt night, with Bread and Beverage. After that was ſerved us, we were roped together, in readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to march; our ſick men were likewiſe crouded into two Carts: About Ten of the Clock we march'd hence four Leagues, we march'd to a Town call'd <hi>Porſarick;</hi> here we made a ſtop in the ſtreets for about half an hour; in the mean time ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral women came to us, and diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted among us their Aprons full of Grapes, and took great pity on us; [we were often, and in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, much pitied by many of the tender Sex]: At laſt we were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted to a great ſtable, that held moſt of us that were well in health, and the reſt were put into another ſtable with the ſick men; they gave us nothing for Supper, ſaving one ſmall Loaf, worth about Six <hi>Deniers,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ever a drop of drink, and if we call'd for any water, in came the Rogues our Guards, and would fall to drubbing us with their drawn Swords moſt furiouſly; I was at this time moſt bitterly inflamed to ſee their barbarous uſage, and withal be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very thirſty, walked with my Mate to the door, deſiring them to do that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:96857:13"/>favour, as to give me a little water, but I partly gueſs'd before what would be the effect of it; in comes one of the Guard, and ſalutes me over the Head and Shoulders with his drawn Sword, and withal gave me a prick on the Arm; the lights being all out, I took him a good box under the ear, and ſtruck him down to the ground, and then I ſeconded it with a kick on the guts; that done, up he gets, and away he runs to call in the reſt of the Guards; but I immediately ſlunk into a hole; in comes the Guards with Swords drawn, and Guns cockt, looking to ſee if they could find who it was that ſtruck the Corporal, but could not find him, by reaſon it was done in the dark, and I my ſelf lay down, as if I had been faſt aſleep. This night they were very fearful of our riſing againſt them; ſo the Mayor of the Town was brought to us, to examine the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs; to him we made our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint; he to appeaſe us, promiſed that we ſhould have a good Supper, and all things neceſſary, as Wine, and Straw to lye on, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that done, away he goes, and preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſtead of performing his promiſe, he forthwith orders a ſtrong Guard to be ſet round the houſe, both within and without, and this was all we got of Mr. Mayor, he being very like the reſt of his Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, <hi>viz.</hi> great and notorious Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars, and deceivers of men. Cloſe by my ſide was poſted a Centi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, a poor innocent fellow, who not long after he was placed there, fell faſt aſleep; I having juſt at my Entry a good view of a Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rooſt, went with my Mate, and each of us got a very good Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let; that done, down we came to our places, without any noiſe, putting our Poultrey into the knees of our Breeches; our Guard at the ſame time was faſt aſleep on the Ground, and with eaſe might any man have diſarm'd him, but alas his looks did ſhew him to be a poor Innocent Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and by that means we let him alone.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturday,</hi> 14. Early this morning we made ready to march, all the Town Guards that watcht us laſt Night, going with us: Before we got out of the Town, at the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble door where the reſt of our men lay, we ſaw the dead body of one of our men upon a ladder, whoſe name was <hi>Alexander Montgome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry:</hi> Away we march'd; and when we had opportunity on the Road, we pickt our Fowls. This part of the Countrey is very mountainous, and yet abounds with plenty of Vineyards and Olive-yards: On the very ſcraggy Rocks and Mountains, grow great plenty of ſweet Herbs, ſuch as Thyme, and Lavender, Roſemary, Mirtles, and other odo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riferous Herbs. This morning two of our men did get out of the Rope, and ſo ſlipt into the cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of a Mountain, and knockt off their Irons, and went away undiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered by any of the Guards. After we had marched three Leagues, we came to a lone Inn by the Road
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:96857:14"/>ſide, near a Town called <hi>Puzola;</hi> we were here conducted into our old Halls, the ſtinking Stables; here we got our Fowls dreſt, and made a great Feaſt; we gave four parts in five to the poor ſick men, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were not able to get up and down, and help themſelves, they would not ſuffer them to come out of the Carts from Morning till Night, but ſat there all Weathers that blew; they gave us here for dinner a ſmall bit of <hi>Pork,</hi> with Bread and Beverage: As ſoon as we had Din'd, we march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out, and being counted out, as was their uſual manner, they miſt two of the number, which were the Two that got away; they counted us over at leaſt ſix times, but when they found that two Men were gone, the Provoſt, with the reſt of them, was in a deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Rage, ſwearing by all their gods, that they would travel us to death; and when we could march no longer, they ſwore they would ſhoot us, and let us lye dead on the Road: But alas! all their ſwearing at us was but to ſmall effect; for although many of our people ſaw them when they went, yet no Man would ſay any thing of it to them, for fear leſt they might be cloſely purſued, and ſo taken; and if they ſhould be taken again by any of theſe Rogues, it were better for them they had never been born. Away we marched one League, to a lone Houſe, by the which was a cloſe place, wherein they uſed to keep Sheep, into this place were we drove, ſick and well, all together; when we came in, we found it to be a moſt loathſome place, full of Sheps-dung, and the Dung full of Maggots; there was no place for any Air to come in to us, ſaving a ſmall hole or two in the Wall. Before Morning we were moſt of us well-near ſtifled, what with the ſtink, and for want of air toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Our Supper here was a piece of Bread and a Cup of Beverage; when our Supper was ſerved us, the Houſe was beſet all round with a ſtrong Guard.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sunday</hi> 15. About Six in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we ſat forth out of this place, the Morning Rainy, with all the Guard that guarded us laſt Night, which were about Fifteen in number, beſides our uſual Guard, which were about Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Horſe and Foot; we marched Three Leagues, to a Town called <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſta,</hi> and all was very foul; when we came to <hi>Capiſta,</hi> which is a fine Walled Town, we walked almoſt round the Town before they could find an empty Stable big enough to hold us; at laſt they found a Stable that held us all, and would have held as many more, if there had been ſo many more of us: Here they gave us our Dinner, which was a piece of Bread worth Six <hi>Deniers,</hi> and about half an ounce of Fat <hi>Pork,</hi> with a Cup of Beverage <hi>per</hi> Man. Dinner was no ſooner ended, but away we marched; We had been on the Road not much above an hour before it began to Thunder, Lighten, and Rain, as if Heaven and Earth would have met; along we marched through thick and thin for the ſpace
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:96857:14"/>of three hours in this ſad Weather: (the Water runningout of the Knees of our Breeches) until we came to a fine fenced Town on the top a Hill, called <hi>Beſias,</hi> Three Leagues diſtant from <hi>Capiſta:</hi> When we came near the Town, we that were before ſtayed for thoſe behind, which were quite foundred; thus in this wet condition we ſtayed in the Road near half an hour in the Rain, until that they were come up to us: That done, we entered the Town, and were put, as near as I can judge, into the Town-Hall; here we ſtaid near Two Hours in this wet condition, as thick and cloſe one by another as we could well ſtand; at laſt we were carried out of this place through the Rain, the Spouts of the Houſes running, or rather pouring on our Heads for the ſpace of half a Mile, and in this wet condition were we drove into a large cold Stable, where we had nothing to lye down on but the cold Ground, and the wet Horſe-Dung, our Cloaths being as wet on our backs, as if we had been plunged in a River, and could not get one rag off our backs, becauſe of our Irons. For Supper we had a ſmall Loaf of Bread, with about half a mouthful of Meat; the quantity of the Meat, I am ſure, was not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to give a <hi>Jack-Daw</hi> a meal, and that which was of it was moſt part Bullocks-Liver and Lights. The Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that brought it in to us, brought it in a Earthen-pan under her Arm, covered with another Earthen Pan; ſo that any one may judge whether Meat for Two Hundred Men could well be carried in the nature afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid: With our Bread and Meat, and each Man a Cup of prick'd Wine, we made our Supper; that done, we lay all down to ſleep on the wet ground.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monday</hi> 16. The Morning, and all the reſt of the Day being Rainy, we continued ſtill in this Stable; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Ten in the Morning they gave us ſome dry Straw, when we had little need of it, our Cloaths be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing almoſt dry on our backs by the heat of our bodies; in this Stable ſome of our Men found out a door that entered into a Wine-Cellar, in which was a Butt of ſpecial ſtrong Wine, into which Cellar a little <hi>French</hi> — Boy and others got in, and handed out to the Men all their Pots and Jars full of this good Wine, which did ſo heat and comfort ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them, that they ſoon forgot ſorrow. In fine, before it was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, we had drank out the beſt part of the Wine. Our Dinner was to Day, a ſmall Loaf <hi>per</hi> Man, and about a mouthful of boiled Guts, and Lights, and Liver, and half a pint of ſowre Wine; for Supper a Loaf and Wine: This day died a Man named <hi>Francis Evans</hi> a Carpenter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tueſday</hi> 17. About 10. this Morning we came out of the Stable into an open place, and being all roped together, we in our uſual manner were ſerved ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, which was Bread and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verage. Twenty five of our Sick-Men we left here in their Hoſpital, and yet
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:96857:15"/>we had at leaſt Twenty Five or Thirty more that were ſick and weak. We marched from this place Four Leagues, to a Town call'd <hi>Pezeain,</hi> a very fine wall'd Town, ſtanding in a very fine level place, and well Moated round. Into this Town we entred, and were put into a very large Stable, well littered with Straw. For Supper, we had our uſual Allowance of Bread, and Pork, and Beverage; ſo here we had a very good Nights-Lodging.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wedneſday</hi> 18. We being roped to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and counted, as was their uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al manner, we marched four Leagues, to a Town call'd <hi>Diſhean,</hi> where we went into a Stable, and had for our Dinner Bread and Beverage, with a little bit of Pork, of about an ounce weight. From thence we marched three Leagues, to a Town called <hi>Punian,</hi> where we took up our Lodging in a Stable; our Supper was Bread and Beverage: So we ſlept in the Stable on wet Horſe-Dung. In the middle of the Night it began to rain ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry faſt, the Stable not being well covered, the rain came down upon us, and almoſt floated us: Thus, and ſuch like, was our Lodging in this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thurſday,</hi> 19. The Weather being ſtill rainy, we continued ſtill in this Stable all this day: We had ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Prieſts and Gentry came to gaze on us; who gave us no comfort, but derided us, our King and Religion: Telling us withall, that King <hi>James</hi> had routed General <hi>Schomberg</hi> in <hi>Ireland;</hi> and moreover, that next Summer, <hi>England</hi> alſo was to be theirs. They ſaid alſo to us, <q>Your condition is here very bad, but if you were in <hi>England,</hi> your caſe would be far worſe; for ſays they, There is at preſent a very ſore Famine, and no Bread hardly to be had for any Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</q> By this I did conjecture, that they had in their Countrey a Lying-Oracle, and that Truth to them was a great Stranger. We were obliged to give them the hearing of all their Stories, although we did not believe one word they ſaid. They gave us here for Dinner a piece of Bread, and a ſmall bit of Mutton, with Beverage; but ſo ſmall was the quantity of Mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, that one Man might very well have eaten twenty Mens ſhares: So that of that little they gave, bread was nine parts in ten of our Proviſion: The reſt was not worth the naming; our Beverage was ſometimes pretty good in thoſe places where they could get no bad Wine; but many times it was worſe than Water. For Supper they gave us Bread and Beverage; and the Water they boild their Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty-Pork in, under the Name of Bon-Supper: This was our Fare; ſo here we ſlept this Night alſo, in the ſame Stable, on the Wet — Horſe-Dung.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:96857:15"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Friday</hi> 20. Early in the Morning the ſick Men were put into two Carts, and the reſt of us being roped together and counted, began to march, wading through ſeveral Rivers, whoſe Depth took us up to the Belly, the Stream running ſo ſwift with the Freſhes of the laſt great Rain, that it was like to overſet our weak Bodies: but our being forty or fifty in a Rope, the one held up the other. As we paſt along by the Road ſide we had leave to enter into the Vineyards and gather Grapes, which we did plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully. Many Vineyards in this Country lie as open to the Road, as many Commons do in <hi>England</hi> or elſewhere. We marched about four Leagues before we came to <hi>Mom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellier,</hi> which is as fine a wall'd Town, and as curiouſly ſituated as ever I beheld a Town in my Life, the bigneſs of the City I do verily belive to be about the bigneſs of the City of <hi>Briſtol;</hi> but about it is a far more pleaſant Landskip, having about it ſeveral curious Champion Hills, and fine Vine-yards and Olive-yards, and about four or five Mile to the Southward of the Town is the fair Mediterranean Ocean, <hi>viz.</hi> the Bay of <hi>Languedock.</hi> When we came near the Town, we were put into a very large Stable, without the Walls of the Town. This Country is the beſt fitted with large Stables of all the places that ever I was in in all Chriſtendom, which have been many. Here it is counted a very ſmall Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that will not hold two Troops of Horſe. And as for their Building, they are built with very much coſt and charge; moſt of them are built of hewn Stone, all arched over head moſt neatly. In this Stable which we were all put in, I took eſpecial notice of one thing that is juſt at every Horſes place all round the Stable: upon the Wall was writ the Name of one Saint or other; what might be the humour of it I cannot gueſs: but this I am certain muſt be the end of the deſign, either for the Horſes to worſhip, or elſe the Oſtler; the Letters were large Capitals. They gave us here for Dinner our uſual Quantity of Pork with Bread, and Beverage; that done, away we march'd two Leagues farther, to a ſmall Village called <hi>Columbeas,</hi> where we were put into two Stables; our Supper was Bread and Beverage; and our Lodging on wet Horſe-dung.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturday</hi> 21. It being a very dreadful Night all the laſt Night for Thunder, Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and Rain, and continued until about eleven this Morning, about which time it began to clear up: ſo here we had our Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, which was a bit of fat Pork of about three quarters of an Ounce Weight, and a piece of Bread, and a Cup of Beverage: that done, we were roped together and counted, and away we marched four Leagues to a Town called <hi>Imergos;</hi> here we were put into a loathſom place where they uſed to keep Sheep in: our Lodging was on the Sheeps Dung, having no Straw at all: ſome of us got the Hurdles to lie on, ſuch as they fold Sheep with, but the moſt part lay on the ground: It would grieve the Heart of a Stone to hear the Groans all Night of our ſick and dying Men which lay in this ſad Condition. Our Supper was a piece of Bread, and a Cup of Beverage, which was far worſe than Water: ſo here we lay until the break of Day.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sunday</hi> 22. We were rouzed very early this Morning out of our ſtinking Den, and being counted like ſo many Sheep, we were roped together, not without many Drubs, for thoſe we had daily and hourly: ſo away we marched for <hi>Cicile.</hi> The People of <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mergos</hi> told our Guards that much of the Country was overflown that we were to paſs through to day, and therefore adviſed them to get Carts to carry us over the deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of the Flouds. According to their advice they got two Carts, which when they came to a ſmall place not above Knee-deep, they
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:96857:16"/>carried us over in the Carts, and ſo diſmiſt the Carts: And within leſs than Piſtol ſhot of this Place, was a Place twice as deep, and ten times the length; over this they made us to wade, which took us up to the middle, and with the ſtrength of the Stream was like to have carried us off the Ground, but that we were roped together in great quantities, ſo we held up one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; thus were we all tantalized with their Carts, making us to wade all the deep Places we came at this day. About two in the Afternoon we came to the Town of <hi>Cicile,</hi> being four Leagues diſtant from <hi>Imergos;</hi> in which Town we were all put into a Stable, where they gave us for Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, Bread and Beverage, ſo we all conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued here until Night; for Supper they gave us Mutton and Broth, but ſo ſmall a quantity was the Mutton, that one Man might eaſily have eat as much as twenty Men had; the Broth they ſerved in ſuch a manner, that he that had not a Cup or Diſh of his own, was forc'd to take his Broth in his Hat or Cap; by this means one of our Men got ſcalded moſt ſadly: At Night the People brought us Straw to lie on, ſo here we got a good Nights Lodging.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monday</hi> 23. In the Morning, about ſix a Clock, we made ready to march (being ſoon dreſs'd) to a City called <hi>Arlaa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> four Leagues diſtance: We paſt moſt of this day through Fenny Land, that was all grown over with Tamaraſs, and by a River ſide: Before we came to <hi>Arlaa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> we croſs'd o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver this River in a Ferry-boat, at three ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times, Sick and Well: On this ſide of the River they diſcharged the Carts which could not paſs over in the Ferry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boats; we that were well, march'd about a Mile to the Town, but thoſe that were ſick lay on the Ground until ſuch time as they had got Carts to bring them to the Town. Before we entered the City of <hi>Arlaa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> we paſs'd over a Bridge made with Boars, and ſo mored in the River, Head and Stearn, over which paſs'd all their Carriage, ſuch as Carts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This Town of <hi>Arlaa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> is a very fine Town; and cloſe by the Walls runs the River, and in the River is much Craſt, ſuch as Settees and Tartans, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This River is that which divides <hi>Languedock</hi> from <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vence.</hi> When we had paſt almoſt through the Town, at the Eaſtermoſt end, they put us into a Stable, and gave us Bread and Beverage for Dinner; ſeveral of our Men that had no Money, being almoſt ſtarved with their ſad Allowance, did proteſt joint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they would not march out of this Stable, unleſs they would give them more Victuals; and if their Law would bear them out to kill them that were their Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners of War, they were willing rather to die by the Sword, than to be ſtarved and travelled to death. They hearing our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, gave us our Supper here; which was pretty conſiderable, a Souſe Loaf, and about an ounce and half of Pork, with Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verage, which was large Allowance to what they uſed to give us: So here we lay all Night, being well guarded by the Town Guards, who were indifferent civil to us, admitting us to go forth to eaſe our ſelves; which we took as a great kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, being moſt an end denied that ſmall Priviledg, but made us eaſe our ſelves where we lay.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tueſday</hi> 24. Early in the morning we marched out of the Town of <hi>Arlaa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>;</hi> the way was level, but extream ſtony. Juſt as we parted with the Town, we paſſed through a Burying-place, where we ſaw hundreds of Tombs hewn out of ſolid Stones of a vaſt breadth and length, moſt of them between 8 and 9 foot long, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with a Stone of a vaſt weight: The People of this place did tell us, that this Town was anciently the Seat of their Kings; and by the infinite quantity of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:96857:16"/>Tombs, we could conjecture no leſs: which may ſignify that much Gentry did attend the Place, as is uſual in the Court of Kings: This is the firſt Town we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred in <hi>Provence;</hi> we marched 3 Leagues unto a lone Houſe, where there was no En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment to be had for us, nor ſcarce any thing to be had for Money: Here our grand Driver, or Provoſt, gave us five Souſe a Man, in a place where nothing fitting for Men was to be had; we were forc'd to give them their own price, what they plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ask, for mouldy Horſe-bread, or any thing elſe that the Houſe would afford. After our Dinner was ended, we marched full five Leagues to the Town of <hi>Sealoon;</hi> the way was extraordinary level, though very ſtony; ſo that for the ſpace of five Leagues, we paſt by but one or two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. About ſeven in the Evening we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred the Town of <hi>Sealoon;</hi> our entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment here was very bad, not for any want there was in the Place, but through the barbarouſneſs of the People; we were all put into a large Stable, Sick and Well al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together; and for every thing we had, we paid double the price: When we had got what we could, we went to ſleep on the hot Horſe-dung, like ſo many Swine, having a great Guard both within and without.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wedneſday</hi> 25. Early in the Morning we made ready to march, the Sick were put in two Carts; many being in a manner dead, thoſe they hailed out by the Legs, and by the Throats; many of them were ſo weak, that they were not able to feed themſelves; yet theſe Wretches would not deſiſt, but kept drubbing them daily and hourly with their Swords, and punching them with the muzzle of their Guns. We marched three Leagues to a ſingle Houſe by the Road ſide; the way very mountanous: at this fingle Houſe we ſat down, and got our Dinner, which was a brown Loaf, and half a pint of Beverage. From hence we marched three Leagues, to a great Town called <hi>Anis;</hi> we were no ſooner entred into the Town, but were conducted to a very large Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the Mobile thronging about us, ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing at us; we were ſcarcely entred into the Stables, but ſeveral Stones were hove in at the Windows, one of them cut one of our Men through the Lip; here we were barbarouſly uſed; our Supper was a Souſe Loaf, and about half an ounce of ſalt Cheeſe, with a cup of Beverage Wine; we ſlept here like ſo many Hogs on the hot Horſe-dung.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thurſday</hi> 26. About ten in the Morning they put the Sick into the Carts; thoſe that were not able to help themſelves, were moſt miſerably drubb'd, hailing them along on the ground like ſo many dead Dogs, to the Carts, and there beat them in a moſt dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful manner; one of our Men that was thus ſerved, died within an hour after he was put into the Cart: We that were well, were roped together after our uſual man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; and away we marched, the People many of them hooping and ſcoffing, and the Boys throwing Stones at us: The Rogues, our Guards, had given us ſuch a Character of Rebels, that had rebell'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our <hi>Righteous King,</hi> as they call'd him, that the People thought verily, I ſuppoſe, that we were worſe than Devils; and withal told them, that we were going to the Gallies: We march'd about two Leagues and an half to a lone Houſe, where we ſate down and eat Bread, thoſe that had Money bought Wine, and to thoſe that had none, our Guardian gave a Souſe-worth of Wine between two Men; our Bread we brought with us from <hi>Ais;</hi> hence we marched 3 Leagues to a Town call'd <hi>Reca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valia;</hi> the way was very mountainous and bad for Carts: When they came to any ſteep Hill, this was their manner, they made faſt all the Sick to the Carts-Arſe with Ropes,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:96857:17"/>with a Man following them, whipping them along, left they ſhould hang on the Cart to eaſe themſelves. This was the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod they uſed with our ſick Men. About ſeven at Night we came into the Town of <hi>Recavalia:</hi> here we were put into two Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles (here in the Night our Men came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Hen-Rooſts, and got ſeveral Hens, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) They gave us for Supper a ſmall Loaf, and about half an Ounce of ſalt Cheeſe, with a Cup of Beverage. In this place they buried the Man that died that day in the Cart: they gave us in this place a little Straw to cover the wet Horſe-Dung: Theſe People that were our Guard were ſo abuſeful to us all Night, that we that were near them could not ſleep all Night for the Noiſe they made of flouting and laughing at us, and calling us ill Names.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Friday</hi> 27. We being roped together and counted, according to uſual manner, we marched three long Leagues to a lone Houſe by the Road ſide: the way was very moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainous, and the ſaid Mountains all over-ran with pine Trees, ſo that here much Roſin is made. When we came into this lone Houſe, they gave us Bread with about half an Ounce of fat Pork, with a Cup of ſour Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verage Wine. Our Men here pick'd up Sticks; and in their drinking Pots they boil'd the Poultry they got laſt Night. After we had dined we marched two long Leagues to a Town called <hi>Pruſſia,</hi> where we lay in two Stables very well littered with Straw: they gave us for Supper a ſouſe Loaf and one Onion <hi>per</hi> Man. The Towns-People were here indifferent civil to us, by admitting us every one, one after another, to go forth and eaſe our bodies, which we always took as a great favour, and very ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom obtained.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturday</hi> 28. We ſet out of this Town very early in the Morning, and we marched two Leagues to a Town called <hi>Olivera,</hi> a fine large Town; here we dined, our Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was a Souſe Loaf and two Sirdenas a Man, with each Man a Cup of Beverage. In this Town died <hi>John Wall,</hi> a Lad of about ſixteen Years of Age, whom theſe barbarous Villains had been beating not above an Hour before, for no other cauſe than this, The poor Lad being cramb'd into the Cart amongſt the reſt of the ſick, when the bitter Pains of Death was upon the poor Soul, he ſeemed to ſtruggle for eaſe, and to get a little more room in the Cart; this was all the occaſion. Now after he was taken dead out of the Cart, for fear leſt he ſhould not be dead, one of the beaſts that guarded us, run his Sword into the Belly of him, and ſo left him to be buried by the Towns-People. Dinner being ended, away we marched for <hi>Toloun,</hi> being about a League diſtant. The Afternoon proved rainy, and the way very bad. About four in the Afternoon we came near the Town, but not ſuffered to enter; we were imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately ſent aboard of an old Man of War of theirs, which lay in the Mold, where we found about ſixty Engliſh Men, which were Priſoners of War, who were taken in the Mediterranean Seas, and about two hundred Dutch: When we were got aboard, they gave us orders to knock off our Irons, which we did forthwith, and hove many of them into the Mold: The Scrivan belonging to the Ship took all our Names, and the Ships Names we were taken in, and our places of Reſidence: which done, we were meſt, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Men together in a Meſs; and ſo for Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per we had Bread and good Wine, half a Pint <hi>per</hi> Man, which was pretty conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to what we uſed to meet with. Our ſick Men, which were forty in number, were put aboard of a Fly-boat which was laſh'd aboard the other Ships: and this they called the Hoſpital Ship; but it were more proper to call it a Slaughter-Houſe; for the poor ſick Men the major part of them had no other Lodging but the bare hard Decks.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:96857:17"/>Their Food was ſomething bettter, although much leſſer than the well-People had, <hi>viz.</hi> Mutton and Broth every day. The Doctors that had charge of the poor ſick Men were the Chyrurgions of the Ships that they took here, ſome Engliſh and ſome Dutch; but whether it were through Ignorance or Idleneſs, or both, or for want of good Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, I am ſure the Men died here ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry faſt, ſometimes two, three, or four a day out of that number aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sunday</hi> 29. It ſo hapned that he that was Captain of the Guard for this Day, was one of my Dear Joys: who makes an Oration about the Ship for all thoſe that were Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholicks to go aboard the Admiral with him to Maſs; but amongſt our Crew there was but one, and that proved to be the Captains dear Country-Man, which I ſpake of before at <hi>Tholuſe:</hi> but amongſt the Dutch there were ſeveral Romans. The Captain promiſed great matters to his Country-Man, what he would do for him for his Country and Religion ſake; but to my Knowledg he forgot to perform any thing of it. When Maſs was over, and the Men come aboard, we were ſerved our Break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt and Dinner, all under one double A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance of Bread and Wine, and of Meat only one Allowance, which although it was but ſmall, yet was it very conſiderable to what we ever met with yet in <hi>France;</hi> for the Bread and Wine were both very good; and as for the Meat, it did exceed the Weight very ſeldom of an Ounce, or an Ounce and half, or thereabouts: But this was the Order in the Morning, every Man had a Loaf and very near half a Pint of Wine; at Dinner the like, and Meat too if it were Fleſh-day; and ſo the ſame for Supper, Bread and Wine, and either Beans Peaſe, Riſe, or Callavanſis: and thoſe days that were Fiſh-days, becauſe of the Scarcity of Fiſh, they gave us either Beans, Peaſe, or Callavanſis, inſtead thereof. Our Diet was very well amended, but our Lodging was on the bare Decks: But as for thoſe Priſoners of Engliſh and Dutch that were here before, they had all Hammocks and Ruggs to lie on. The Dutch here ſeeing of us very poor in Habit, and weak in body, began to inſult over us, in pretending we ſhould ſtay till they were ſerved their Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als every day, before we were ſerved: but as ſoon as we diſcovered their Ambition, we fell to work with them, and for all they thought to have been too ſtrong for us, yet were they deceived, for we ſoon put them to the Rout, and made them take turns to be ſerved, one firſt one Day, and the other the other Day. The Iriſh Captain would very often make an Oration to us, requiring of us to be loving and kind one to the other: and as we were Fellow-Priſoners to be quiet together; but it was ſoon ordered by the Intendant, that there ſhould be another Ship brought alongſt this Ship-ſide for the Engliſh-Men to be in by themſelves; for while the Engliſh and the Dutch were toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Dutch would neither pump the Ship which was very leaky, nor go in the Boat to fetch Water, or any thing elſe aboard; ſuch was their Pride, that tho I had ever much Charity for the Dutch before, yet I was ſorry to ſee them ſo arrogant. But that day that the Ship was to be mored by the other, which was the third day of <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> there came an Expreſs from <hi>Paris,</hi> that all the Engliſh Priſoners ſhould be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried back into <hi>Weſt-France,</hi> in order (as they ſaid) to be exchanged. But in the mean time they took theſe Methods to keep our Men at work, that fifty every day they ſent aboard of a Fly-boat Man of War, much like the <hi>King-Fiſher,</hi> there they ſerved and fitted ſtanding Rigging for their Ships, but as for wages they had none: Others they ſent aſhore to the Rope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>walk, to lay Cables to them; for their days work they were paid four Souce a day:
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:96857:18"/>Another Gang was ſent aboard of a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant's Ship belonging to ſome of the Grandees of the Place, to heave out her great Stone Ballaſt, and make her fit to Careen: Their Wages was three Souſe and a half a day. Another Gang of Carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were drawn out to go to Calk this Ship's ſide; to them they gave ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Souſe a day. Thus Neceſſity forced us to do that, ſhrewdly againſt our wills. In this place of <hi>Touloun,</hi> Sea-men were ſo ſcarce, that by the Report of the People, there were not Twenty in the place; as for my part, I never ſaw ten whilſt I was there. Their own Carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were now fitting out ten Sail of Ships to be ready to come down into <hi>Weſt-France</hi> next Spring, and ten Sail is the moſt that is here left, which will be any way fit for the Sea. The Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral is a curious fine Ship to look to, but ſhe is broken-back'd, and not fit for the Sea; thoſe Ships that are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of coming to Sea, are Ships of good Force, from Fifty to Seventy Guns. We heard, whilſt we were here, that the French had lately forced many of the Dutch Priſoners of War to go to Sea in the Cruſers, by heaving them off their Gunnil into the Boat, if they did not go themſelves into the Boat: And ſince, the Ships which had theſe Men in them are taken, many of them into <hi>Algier,</hi> and are now made Slaves; which Action is contrary to the Law of God and Nature. The Weather being very bad as yet, we could not begin our Journey until the tenth day of <hi>October;</hi> in the mean time we buried many of our Men, and yet many more left Sick. We heard, after our depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that they ſent all our Men, both Sick and well, to the Hoſpitals, to ſtrengthen and refreſh them, left there ſhould be none left to travel back, which was very true, as I heard it repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by many of the Men when they came back to <hi>Rochfort:</hi> There were two hundred more that came here, ten days after our departure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:96857:18"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>From</hi> Toulon <hi>to</hi> Rochfort.</p>
               <p>October.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>THurſday</hi> 10. About ten in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Weather being fair, all the Engliſh that were able to march, were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded on Shore: So entring the Town, we were brought to one of the French King's Magazines, where we were all cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led over by Name: In the <hi>interim,</hi> in comes the Intendant, and makes an Oration to us, which was Engliſhed thus; Swearing by all his Gods, that we were clear Men, only we were to travel to <hi>Rochfort,</hi> and from thence to St. <hi>Malo,</hi> where we were to be exchanged. We deſired him, (by the way of an Interpreter) that ſince his Excellency was pleaſed to ſay we were clear Men, that we might travel back with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being afflicted with Ropes and Irons, which we ſaw lay ready for us, and about ſix couple were already ironed; we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed upon our Faith, that we would march quietly through the Country, without running away: He granted our Requeſt, alledging, we were clear Men. As ſoon as we came into <hi>Weſt-France,</hi> we all gave great credit to his words, not doubting but that a Man of his Rank and Dignity would ſcorn to tell us (who were at preſent his Priſoners, and lay at his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, to do with us as he pleaſed) Lies: But we after found his Words to be like the reſt of his lying Country-men, (who are the greateſt Liars upon Earth); I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard Word or Promiſe made by any of them, ſince I have been in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, that proved to be true, except it were when they promiſed to plague us. The Intendant ordered to thoſe that were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt naked (that were many) to have Canvaſe Jackets, and to ſome Shirts, and the major part new Shoes. After theſe things were ſerved, away we march'd, having for our Guard, four of the Guarda-Marine, (who wears a Belt em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broidered with Gold and Silver, the Flower-de-Luce, and the Croſs Anchors and Cables, which is their Commiſſion) beſides the Provoſt and two Foot Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers. When we came to the outer Gates of the Town, we ſtopt about two hours, waiting for more Company, which were the Men that were taken in the <hi>Mediter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranean</hi> Seas, belonging to Capt. <hi>Willbourn</hi> and Capt. <hi>Blake,</hi> their Number was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſixty: So now we were near two hundred of us. About three in the After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon we went out of <hi>Toulon,</hi> we mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched three long Leagues to a Town call'd <hi>Pruſſia;</hi> it was very near eight at Night be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we came into this Town; yet we marched along briskly, although the Road was hilly and ſtony, we were in hopes the Intendant's words would prove true; our Guards were ſomewhat civiller than they were before; neither was there ſuch ſtrict Orders given to thoſe that guarded us by Night as before, for we were now admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to go forth at any hour of the Night to eaſe our ſelves, if it was required: They gave us here for our Supper each Man a ſmall Loaf of ſix Denires, and a cup of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:96857:19"/>Wine; ſo here we ſlept very well, the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble being indifferently well littered.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Friday</hi> 11. About ſeven a Clock in the Morning we came out of the Stables, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man receiving a Loaf of ſix Denires, (which is half a Peny Engliſh); the place we were to dine at this day, being a lone Houſe, where Bread was not to be had for ſuch a Company of Men: Three Leagues we marched to this lone Houſe, the way very Mountainous; when we came there, they gave each Man a cup of ſour Wine, and that with our ſmall Loaf we brought with us, we made up our Dinner: After this we marched three large Leagues to a Town called <hi>Racavalia;</hi> after about an hours ſtop in the Streets, we were put into two Stables: For our Suppers, they gave each Man a Souſe Loaf, and a diſh of Pork<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broth: now when they came to ſerve us the Meat we expected, they gave not one Man in ten any; it was my chance to get a bit ſo ſmall, that I could have put twice as much into my Mouth at once: and as for our Drink, it was down-right Vinegar, that no Man was able to drink it: Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though good Wine was ſo plentiful here, and ſo cheap, that it was not worth above one Crown the Hogſhead by whole-ſale: The Vinegar they gave us, we ſet it out at the Door, and drank Water, a Brook running juſt at the Stable-door: We bore all this with patience, hoping once, if it pleaſed God, to get out of theſe Rogues hands; ſo we went to ſleep quietly in theſe Stables.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturday</hi> 12. Early in the Morning we came out of theſe Stables; every Man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a ſix Denire Loaf as he paſt, for we were to dine to day at a ſingle Houſe: Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of our Men that were foundred in their Feet got Aſſes, ſome upon their own coſt, and ſome upon their charge that guarded: ſo away we marched two Leagues to this lone Houſe; there with our Bread and a Cup of Beverage we made our Dinner, which was very little for poor Men to travel with ſo far as twenty and twenty four Miles a day, and many times more: We ſaw moſt part of this Morning the <hi>Alps,</hi> that divide <hi>Italy</hi> from <hi>France</hi> very plain, bearing about Eaſt North Eaſt, and North Eaſt from us: From hence we marched three Leagues to the City of <hi>Ais,</hi> the way very moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainous, but the Mountains were all over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran with ſweet Herbs, ſuch as Thyme, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vender, Roſemary, Mirtles, and the Hedges of Pomgranates, which caſt a very ſweet Odour. When we came near the City, we were put into a large Stable without the Walls: This <hi>Ais</hi> is a very fine ſcituated Place, and the City laid out in excellent order, being built in a level place, and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumdated with Hills all round: they gave us here for our Supper a ſmall Loaf of Bread, and about half an Ounce of ſalt Cheeſe, and to each Man was meaſured half a pint of good Wine, for no bad Wine here was to be got, or elſe to be ſure we had had it. After we had ſupp'd, we laid us down to ſleep on the Ground, but many of us got ſome Hay and ſome Straw: we had here, as at other places, a Guard of the Towns-People that watch'd over us all Night.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sunday</hi> 13.</p>
               <p>This Morning our Guards went all to Maſs, and by that means we were all kept in until eleven of the Clock, at which time they gave us our Dinner of Bread and Wine. When our Dinner was ended, away we marched five long Leagues to a Town called <hi>Sealoon.</hi> The Afternoon proved rainy, and the Road very foul. Before we got into Town it was eight at Night. Moſt part of us being wet through thoſe few
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:96857:19"/>Rags we had. This Town is a very fine wall'd Town, ſcituated at the bottom of the Provencial Hills, having on the South, Weſt and North part of the Town a great Plain near thirty Miles long, which in compariſon of Land, is as level as the Sea; yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Land is very ſtony and full of large peble Stones, much like a Beach, and by that means very barren: yet ſweet Herbs grow wild upon it, ſuch as Thime and Lavender; and in the Plain ſome Wood of the ever-living Oak. We were here put all into one Stable, where they gave us for Supper Bread and Wine; and the Stable was very well littered with Straw; ſo we ſlept very ſweetly all Night, having a great Guard about us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monday</hi> 14.</p>
               <p>Early this Morning we came out of this Stable, every Man received a ſix Denier Loaf as he paſs'd, becauſe we were to dine at a ſingle Houſe upon the Plain: We marched five Leagues over this Plain, before we came to this lone Houſe, at the end of which they gave each Man a Cup of Wine and Water to our Bread. When Dinner was ended, away we marched three Leagues farther, to the City of <hi>Arlaa.</hi> Before we entred this Town, we heard that there were in the Town two hundred of Engliſh and Dutch Priſoners of War, onward of their March for <hi>Toulon.</hi> This News ſtruck ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of us into a damp, thinking that this was not the way to be exchanged. When we came into Town, we were all cramb'd into a Stable, where we lay deſperate thick, one almoſt upon the other. One of our Men got leave of the Guards to go where theſe other Priſoners were, to ſpeak to them; who when he came there, he ſaw ſeveral of our ſick Men which we left upon the Road, which were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered; they were all in the ſame dreſs as we were in, as we went for <hi>Toulon, viz.</hi> in Irons, two and two together: They alſo reported, that they were far worſe pinch'd for Victuals than we were: and as for their ſick Men, they were worſe ſerved; for when their weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was ſo great that they could not fit upon an Horſe, or Aſs, then were they thrown thwart a Horſe's back, like a Calf, with their Heads downwards, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til ſuch time that they died. Our Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per here was a ſix Denier Loaf, and a Cup of Beverage a Man. So here we ſlept upon the Horſe-dung, for want of Litter; for except it were the Charity of the People to give it to us, we very ſeldom had any.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tueſday</hi> 15.</p>
               <p>About ten in the Morning we ſaw the Engliſh and the Dutch Priſoners which lay in this Town laſt Night paſs by here: So we ſpoke to ſeveral of them which were of our Company which we left ſick upon the Road, they march'd near the manner as we did formerly, as we were going upward towards <hi>Toulon:</hi> We remained in this Town until two in the Afternoon; at which time they gave us our Dinner, which was a ſmall Loaf of Bread, and an Onion, with a Cup of Beverage a Man. This place of <hi>Arlaa</hi> is a very fine fenced Town, ſtanding on level Ground; and in it are very ſtately Buildings. On the Eaſt ſide of the Town is a moſt famous Aquaduct, which ſtands up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on abundance of Arches; and for the length of it, I ſuppoſe it may be near a Mile. At this time the Land about the Town was much overflown with the Freſhes that came lately down out of the Hill-Country; ſo that in the green Fields that were, as we paſt by here before, we ſaw many Boats and Nets ſet to catch Fiſh,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:96857:20"/>for the Water was conſiderable deep; and beſide, the ſtrength of the Floods had car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away the Town-bridg that was built upon Boats, as I ſaid before; now the Land being thus drowned, we were forc'd to march round the drowned Land, (our ſick Men came after us by Water in a Boat) upon a very fine Cauſey, which was made on purpoſe: for it ſeems theſe Floods are not unuſual, but common, once a Year in the time of Rain. We marched three Leagues to a fine Town called <hi>Terraſcoon;</hi> there we croſt the River in two Ferry-Boats, to a Town oppoſite, call'd <hi>Boucaro,</hi> in the Province of <hi>Languedock;</hi> for this River, as I have ſaid before, divides <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vence</hi> from <hi>Languedock.</hi> This <hi>Boucaro</hi> is a very large Town; when we were entred into it, we were conducted to a great Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, which was both wet and naſty: Our Supper was a ſmall Loaf of Bread, with a Cup of Beverage; and as we were ſerving, in comes our Sick and Lame People to take part of our hard Night's Lodging: the Ground was ſo wet and cold, that we were forc'd to walk up and down the moſt part of the Night, to keep our ſelves warm, the Weather being very cold.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wedneſday</hi> 16.</p>
               <p>About Eleven in the Morning we had our Dinner ſerved us, which was a Loaf of Bread worth ſix Denires, and one Oni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on betwixt four Men, with a Cup of Beverage; which, as ſoon as we had eat and drank, away we march'd. Juſt as we came without the Town, we met about twelve Men, who were pinioned and bound together, going towards <hi>Boucare,</hi> with a Guard with them. We asked the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the place, what their Fault was that they ſhould be thus led? They made us anſwer, that they were <hi>Hugonots,</hi> or <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> and were going for the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies. This Report made my Heart to ake, to ſee ſo many good-look'd Men to be thus treated, (by a curſed Tyrant of Hell) for their acknowledging and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Doctrine of Jeſus Chriſt. We marched four Leagues to a fine compact fenced Town called <hi>Nimes</hi> in <hi>Langue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dock.</hi> When we came near the Town, I went, with three more of my Conſorts, to a Tavern juſt by, to buy a little Wine: When we came to the Door, the good Man of the Houſe asked us of what Nation we were? we told him, Of the Engliſh, (by one of our Companions that ſpoke very good French, he being a <hi>Guernſey</hi>-Man); away went the good Man of the Houſe, and fetch'd a Pitcher of pure good Wine, and four clean Glaſſes; he gave to each Man a Glaſs full of Wine, which we drank up; he filled the Glaſſes again, ſo we drank each Man his ſecond; the Glaſſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing large, and the Wine very ſtrong, we were afraid to venture upon the other Glaſs: We asked the good Man, what we were to pay? he anſwered us, Nothing; but asked, if we would drink any more? we gave him hearty thanks, and anſwered, No: He again asked, if we were of the Religion of the Church of <hi>England?</hi> we told him, Yes. With that he took us by the Hands, and ſqueezed our Hands, and deſired God to be with us: we admired at the Humour of this Man, not expecting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch kind of People here. As we were returning to the reſt of our Companions, we met with a poor Woman, (by her Dreſs we could imagine no leſs) ſhe had a fine white Cake of Bread in her Apron; ſhe held it out to me, I imagined it had been for me to buy it; but ſhe bad me break and eat, which I did; ſo ſhe handed it amongſt the reſt of our Company, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til it was all gone: I durſt to have ſworn, that by my firſt ſight of this Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that ſhe had been more apter to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:96857:20"/>ask than to relieve. Before we went in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Stable, a very brisk young Man came up to me, who had lived in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> a conſiderable time, and ſpoke Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh very proper; he asked many Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions concerning our Affairs in <hi>England,</hi> for it ſeems here the current News is, that <hi>Schonberg</hi> is routed in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and that the French had defeated our Fleet at Sea. I told him, they had in their Country a damnable lying Oracle; and, <hi>that Knaves they project, and Fools be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve;</hi> but I ſaid, if he had Faith to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve what I ſhould ſay, I muſt, to tell you the truth, tell you quite contrary; for in the firſt place, <hi>Schonberg</hi> hath advanced at a great rate in <hi>Ireland:</hi> And as for your Fleet, they durſt not ſhew their Heads at Sea. I alſo told him, that it was true, the French Fleet were out laſt Summer, but ſtaid but a very little while out, and preſently ran into their Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours again. I alſo told him how our Engliſh Fleet lay againſt <hi>Breſt,</hi> and ſent them in a Defiance. The Man was much taken with my Diſcourſe, but time would not admit of it, for we were drove in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Stables immediately: but before he and I parted, I asked of him what kind of People the People of this place were; he told, that not long ſince the 9/10 of the People were <hi>Calviniſts;</hi> and ſo they were ſtill, although they were forc'd to appear otherwiſe; and that you will find, ſays he, if you ſtay here but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til to morrow about eight of the Clock, as ſoon as People can have notice of you; for as yet we did not enter the Town, neither was it deſigned that we ſhould. When this Man and I parted, he promiſed to ſee me the next Morning; but, alas, he was prevented, for we march'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way hence by that time it was well light, we were here put into a Stable, where we were paid off with a great Supper that they had long promiſed; for our Supper was about a Mouth-full of boild Gut, or a piece of Liver or Lights, with a Loaf worth no more but three Denires; the People of the place report, that the old Woman which ſerved us our Meat, brought it all in a Diſh under her Arm, covered with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Diſh; ſo that it is eaſy to judg how much one Man muſt have, when we were to have no more; each Man had a Cup of Wine: Alſo the Supper being ſoon ended, we went to ſleep, the Stable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very well littered: the Governor of the Town, juſt as we were going to ſleep, ſent his own Guards to guard us; and very ſuſpitious they were, what-ever their Humour was I cannot tell, of our ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Houſe on fire.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thurſday</hi> 17.</p>
               <p>Very early this Morning, before ſcarce any of the Inhabitants were ſtirring, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to march: many of our People got Relief by thoſe People that were up, which were generally the poorer ſort: Away we march'd four long Leagues to a Town called <hi>Lunae:</hi> We came into this Town many of us before our Guards, ſo thoſe walked up and down. The People of this place were very charitable to our People, by relieving them with ſuch things as they had, as Bread, Meat, Wine, Raſins, and to ſome Hats, they alſo told many of us that they were Calviniſts. The major part of the People of the Town withall praying for the Succeſs of the Arms of our King <hi>William,</hi> who fought the Battle of God, (this they ſpoke in private to ſome of us.) Many of our Men by the Liberality of the People, got mellow with Wine. When our Guards came into Town with the reſt of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:96857:21"/>our People, we were confined into a Yard, where they gave us a ſmall Loaf of Bread worth fix Denires, and a Cup of Wine for Dinner; that done, away we marched two Leagues farther, to a Town called <hi>Colum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beas:</hi> About eight at Night we came into this Town, where we were put into four Stables, the Stables being here very ſmall: The Supper we had was Bread and Beve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and a couple of Sirdenaſs's a Man, which was extraordinary. The Stables be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very well littered with Straw, we ſlept very well here; neither was there any Body to guard us, for in this ſmall Town were very few Men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Friday</hi> 18.</p>
               <p>Early in the Morning we came out of this Village, the Weather being fair and clear, our ſick and lame Men were put into two Carts; ſo away we marched two Leagues to the City of <hi>Mompelier:</hi> We walked round the City cloſe by the Walls, but were not admitted to enter thereto, becauſe here are many well-affected Perſons, who wiſh well to our Nation. In the Suburbs of this City we were all put into a great Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, where our Dinner was ſerved us, ſix Deniers worth of Bread, and about half an Ounce of miſerable ſad choaky Cheeſe, with a Cup of Beverage for each Man. When Dinner was ended, away we marched three Leagues farther, to a Village called <hi>Punian:</hi> In our way we met ſeveral Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Foot Souldiers, who came from their Campagainſt the Spaniards in a great Diſorder. We heard by the way that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> had defeated the <hi>French</hi> Army in <hi>Catalonia,</hi> and had taken two eminent Places from them, and were ſtill advancing upon them. When we came into <hi>Punian</hi> the People did not care to come near us; for at the fame time they had the Plague in the Town, which, as they report, we left behind us as we were going to <hi>Toulon,</hi> for in this Place we lodged two Nights and one whole Day, by reaſon of the Rain: We were here lodged in a very cold Stable, where our Supper was a ſmall Loaf, and half an Ounce of Cheeſe with Beverage, as at other times. When we had ſupped we laid us down on the cold Ground to ſleep, but were not able to lie there long; ſo that many of us got up and walked about the beſt part of the Night, to keep our Selves warm. About three in the Morning another Man and I went out of the Stable, where we ſaw a Fire juſt by us, with four French-men fitting round it with their Guns to guard it; we walked towards the Fire, which when theſe poor Fellows ſaw, they called out to us, asking us whither were we going? we told them to the Fire; they bid us keep back, but nevertheleſs we went up to the Fire, which when theſe poor Souls ſaw that we were not affrighted at their Words, which was the utmoſt they durſt do, they preſently got up, and away they went, calling us Bugera's, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and left the Fire to us, ſo here we two ſat by it until we ſat it out, which time it began to be day: now we found that as laſt Night no body would come anear us to let us have any Wine to drink, but what the Guards were forced to fetch a Mile off; ſo by the Virtue of our ill Report, we got a good Fire to warm ſome of us to our ſelves.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturday</hi> 19.</p>
               <p>Before the riſing of the Sun we marched out of this Village, the Morning clear but cold: We marched to a Town call'd <hi>Lupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> marching very near the Sea ſide, and rounding the Bay of <hi>Languedock.</hi> All the Places upon the Road were infected with the Plague. The People as they paſſed by
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:96857:21"/>kept ſtopping their Noſes for fear they ſhould get the Plague of us: and truly our greateſt Plague was, that of their own Country-Men, who drove us up and down until we were almoſt all ſtarved; ſo that the greateſt Diſeaſe we had amongſt our poor Men did proceed from Hunger and Cold, and our ſtinking Lodgings. When we came into <hi>Lupean,</hi> we were conducted to our old Halls the Stables, where our Dinner was a ſmall piece of Bread, and one ſmall Onion, and a Cup of Beverage a Man. From hence we marched three Leagues farther, to a Town called <hi>Pezeain,</hi> a very large Town: (by the Town we ſaw about fifty or ſixty Women carrying Earth in Baskets to make a Bridg over the Low-land, with their O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeers by them, to keep them cloſe at work: This is done for Puniſhment for ſome Malefact committed or ſuppoſed.) Here they were likewiſe infected with the Plague too, and all the Fault was laid upon us, for they all ſay we left it behind us, as we marched this way: We told them no, we left none of our Plagues behind us, for as yet they ſtuck ſo cloſe to us, we could not get rid of any of them. In this Town we were kept up very cloſe in a Stable, no body coming near us but our Guards that tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled with us: here our Supper was no more than ſix Deniers worth of Bread, and half an Ounce of ſad Cheeſe, with a Cup of Beverage a Man; and by reaſon that no body came near us, we found out the place where the Straw lay; we took what we thought fit, and made our Lodging very good: this made well on our ſides.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sunday</hi> 20.</p>
               <p>Early in the Morning we put our ſick and lame into two Carts, each Man receiving a ſix Denier Loaf as we came out. We marched one League and half to a very ſmall Village; there we ſat down and dined, here they gave each Man a Cup of new thick Wine, and that with our Bread made up our Dinner: ſo away we marched two Leagues and a half farther, to the Town <hi>Beſias:</hi> both this days Journey, and that yeſterday, the Land was moſt curiouſly planted with Vineyards and Olive-yards, and beſides moſt of this Province is ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. When we came into the Town, we ſaw ſeveral of our ſick Men which we left here behind us, that were ſomewhat reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered; they were quartered in private Houſes, yet kept ſo cloſe, that what they ſpake to us was out of the Windows: We asked the reaſon why they were put out of the Hoſpitals; they told us becauſe ſo many of their own People, both ſick and wounded came into the Town, who came from the Camp againſt the Spaniards, that they filled the Hoſpitals and more Places beſides; they told us of the Defeat the Spaniards had given them, killing them 1500 Horſe one Morning, beſides Foot. This I heard to be verified by one that was in the Fight, which I ſhall make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of in its place. They told us alſo that the Spaniſh Army was advanced within four Leagues of that Place; and that the Spaniſh Army did conſiſt of eighty Thouſand Men Horſe and Foot, and that of the French ſixty Thouſand: And moreover they told us, of thoſe Men we left here, three were dead, and two more lay a dying, and the reſt that were recovered were carried to <hi>Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> in the laſt Company that paſt this way. We paſt quite through the Town towards the outſide; there we were put into a Stable where we were moſt into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerably throng'd for want of room, yet was there no ſuch Guard over us as in ſome of the other Towns, the People here being more humane, and better
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:96857:22"/>knows the Fortune of War: Our Supper here was very inconſiderable; for unleſs it were Bread, ſome got nothing at all; them that had any more, it was about an Ounce of Liver or Lights, and a Cup of four Wine; ſo we lay moſt deſperately throng'd, not having any room many of us to lye down.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monday</hi> 21.</p>
               <p>About ſeven in the Morning we came out of the Town of <hi>Beſias,</hi> taking along with us three ſick Men of ours, which were ſomething recovered: Away we marched two Leagues to a fine fenced Town called <hi>Capiſta,</hi> in which Town we dined; our Dinner was a ſix Denier Loaf, and about half an Ounce of ſad choaky Cheeſe, with a Cup of Beverage a Man. When Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was ended, away we marched four Leagues and a half to an Inn by the Road ſide near the Town of <hi>Puzola.</hi> In our way we both croſſed and marched a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the Banks of the cut River. In our way we ſaw a number of Women at work, in banking and repairing the Sluſes of the River: The Women ſeeing ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Men paſs by, began to geze at us, but immediately comes their Overſeer, and drives them to work with a Blow over the back. Thus are the People of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try plagued by their King who <hi>Tarquin</hi>-like ſtudies Torments; for the Men Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and for the Women the new River: ſo that he comes but little ſhort of a Plague to all Mankind within his Verge: About eight at Night we came into our Lodging, where we found our Stables well littered with Straw, but I ſuppoſe it was not done for us, but for the Souldiers which paſt by here lately, for the Straw was very louzy. Our Supper was a ſmall Loaf of ſix De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niers price, and about half an Ounce of Cheeſe, like the former, and a Cup of ſad Beverage: With this and ſuch like was our Fare, very ſeldom exceeding the price of two pence half penny a day.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tueſday</hi> 22.</p>
               <p>Before it was day we began our March, every Man receiving a half penny Loaf, as he paſt out of the Stables: away we march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed three Leagues to a Town called <hi>Porſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick;</hi> we no ſooner entred the Town, but we were conducted into a large Stable; where with our. Loaf that was given us in the Morning, and half an Ounce of Cheeſe, and a Cup of Beverage, we made up our Dinner. Our Men this Afternoon began to be diſturbed at their ſhort Feeding; they did proteſt to the Guards that ſerved us, they would go no farther, neither were they able, except they gave us more Food. The Guards go and tell the Provoſt that the Priſoners would not march without more Victuals: Preſently in comes the Provoſt with ſome of the reſt, with Swords drawn, and Piſtols cock'd, ſwearing he would be the Death of that Man that did but refuſe to march: up ſtands two Men and deſired to be heard by the way of an Interpreter: he ſeeing two Men ſpeak, he immediately cuts one of them over the Head, and the other he takes away and commanded to be pinion'd. So in fine both of them were pinioned and made faſt to the Carts Arſe: and after this be began to diſplay his Sword over the back of all near him: I my ſelf was one of the two that was made faſt to the Carts Arſe, and <hi>Henry Robinſon</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he had his Head cut: and I was made faſt with my back towards the Cart, ſo cloſe, that I could not turn my Face, but was forc'd to follow the Cart backwards; and with the ſudden fall of the Cart into Holes, I thought verily with the Jerks, it
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:96857:22"/>would at once have broken both my Arms and Back: Moreover my Arms were pini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned ſo ſtraight, that my Veins in my Hand were ready to burſt: for the ſpace of a League was I forced to walk backwards until we came to a ſmall Town called <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheletto:</hi> When we came to the Town they looſed both me and the other Man; ſo we were all put into a Stable, ſick and well to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; and for our Supper they gave us about an Ounce and half of brown Bread, and that was the moſt of it, with a Cup of Beverage; and they pretended they could get no more; but this was all great Lies, for when they came to never ſo plentiful a place, it did not much differ. In this Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble was a door that opened into a Wine-Cellar, which our Men found a way to open; and ſo went in and filled all their Pots and Jars, and had they not been diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by chance, by a Woman that came and catch'd a Man at it, without doubt they had made clear work.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wedneſday</hi> 23.</p>
               <p>Before the Sun riſing we began our March: our ſick and lame were put into two Carts; but to thoſe that were the moſt helpleſs, the Beaſts would lay them on ſtoutly in their getting up into the Cart. From hence we marched two Leagues to a Town called <hi>Traevis,</hi> in which Town we were put into a Stable, where we were ſerved our Dinner, a ſmall Loaf, and about half an Ounce of Cheeſe like the former, with a Cup of muſty Beverage, far worſe than Water. From hence we marched one League farther, to the Town of <hi>Carkaſona:</hi> And from thence we marched two Leagues farther, to a Village called <hi>Villa Sancto,</hi> in which Village we were put into a moſt loathſom ſtinking Stable: Our Supper was a Piece of Bread and one Onion a Man, and a Cup of ſad Beverage: ſo here we ſlept like ſo many Hogs in this ſtinking place. At Night we were ſhut up ſo cloſe, that not one Man could go out to eaſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, whatſoever Neceſſity he had: this Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledg we were not denied ever ſince we came from <hi>Toulon</hi> until now: I ſuppoſe it was out of Revenge for yeſterdays work at <hi>Porſarick,</hi> in denying to march.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thurſday</hi> 24.</p>
               <p>About Eight this Morning we began our march, according to our uſual man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, without Eating or Drinking. Our Sick were put into two Carts, many of them now almoſt famiſhed with Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Away we marched towards <hi>Villa Picta,</hi> two Leagues diſtant: Upon the Road we met with a Flock of Sheep; and ſo our Men managed their Buſineſs, that they ſingled one Sheep from the reſt, and hove a Rug upon him, and carried him away undiſcovered, both from the Shepherd and our Guards. In our way alſo we met ſeveral fine Troops of Horſe going towards <hi>Beaſias.</hi> When we came into Town, we were put into a Stable; and ſo well our Men managed their Mutton, that it was not diſcovered, tho the Men were told in one by one. Now when they had the Sheep ſafely in, they ſoon kill'd it, and buried the Intrals in the Litter; and ſo cut it into Quarters, and ſhared it amongſt thoſe that were of the Cabal: Our Dinner here was a piece of Bread and a cup of Beverage. So away we marched three Leagues farther, to a Town called <hi>Caſtlelador;</hi> when we came into this Town, it was ſo full of Souldiers, that there were no quarters to be had, ſo that after we had ſat down on the Ground for the ſpace of an Hour in the cold, they got an order to put us into an Hoſpital without the Town: Thoſe Men of ours that were ſick, lay upon Beds here,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:96857:23"/>but as for the reſt, they lay on the cold Stones. Our Supper here was a piece of Bread and two Sirdinaſſes, with a Cup of Beverage a Man: Our Men got ſome part of the Sheep dreſt here, with ſeveral Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets they pick'd up on the Road; ſo the Broath they diſtributed amongſt our poor ſick Men. After we had ſupped, we laid us down to ſleep, but were not able to lie long, ſo up we got and walked about moſt part of the Night to keep our ſelves warm. Mr. <hi>George Winſhuft</hi> was a dying all this Night.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Friday</hi> 25.</p>
               <p>About eight this Morning we began to march, every Man receiving half a Souſe Loaf. As we came out, our ſick Men we put into two Carts. This Morning died Mr. <hi>George Winſhuft,</hi> as ſoon as he was put into the Cart. Away we mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched three Leagues, to a Village call'd <hi>Vinunut;</hi> here we dined; our Dinner was a Cup of very good Wine, which was ſo extream cheap, and no bad Wine to be had, that they were in a manner forc'd to give good Wine againſt their will; for in my ſight they went all over the Village to ſee if they could get any Traſh for us, but could not: So with our Bread and Wine we made up our Dinner. After Dinner we went ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of us to work, where they appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted us to dig a Grave to bury the Man that died this day; ſo we made his Grave, juſt by the Way ſide, whilſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were imployed in ſowing him up in his own Blanket. After we had bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried him, away we marched, two Leagues further, to a Town called <hi>Villa Nova,</hi> where we were lodged in two Stables; our Supper was a piece of Brown Bread, and a Cup of Beverage. The Prieſt of this Place came to us, and diſcourſed one of our Men in Latin: He told him, he had Charity for all Men that were Chriſtians, and therefore he did not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpect us for our Opinion. He ſhewed his Charity to us more than all the Clergy-men in the Country: He told us, he had no Money, but he would ſend us a Pitcher of Wine amongſt two or three of us; the which he did. The Stables being well littered, we ſlept ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well: This Night died <hi>Henry Fullſtone,</hi> Gunner of the <hi>Levantine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturday</hi> 26.</p>
               <p>Early in the Morning we began our march, leaving the dead to be buried by the People. Hence we marched three Leagues to a Town called <hi>Caſtinata:</hi> Here we dined; our Dinner was a ſmall piece of Bread, and two ſmall Sirdenaſſes a Man, with Beverage as at other times: Here they took the Horſes out of the Cart, and laid our ſick and dying Men in the High-way, until we were ready to go. After we had dined, we put our Men up into the Carts; and away we marched, two Leagues further, to the City of <hi>Tholouſe:</hi> When we had ſurrounded a great part of the City Walls, we were put in the ſame Stable without the Town that we were in before. Here were we put, Sick and Well altogether, in this cold wet Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Our Supper here was like our Lodging, a half Souſe Loaf, and one Onion a Man, with a Cup of ſad Beve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage. When we laid down to ſleep, we could not for the Sick and dying Mens Groans. The Rogues that guarded us kept the Door ſhut, that we could not get out to eaſe our ſelves, many of our Men having the Flux; but twice this Night we broke open the Door, and made way for our Sick Men. About twelve this Night died <hi>Peter Holt,</hi> Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penter of the <hi>Levantine.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:96857:23"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sunday</hi> 27. We ſtaid here in this Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble until near two in the Afternoon, hear they gave us our Dinner, which was a Souſe Loaf and about an Ounce of fat Pork, with a cup of Wine: af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we had dined, we made ready to march; ſix Men more were brought into our company, which were left ſick upon the Road, and ſo put into the Hoſpital here. When we marched hence we left two Men dying in the Stable, <hi>viz. Richard Vincent</hi> Carpenter, and <hi>Peter Roſe:</hi> from this Place we marched about three quarters of a Mile, to the River-ſide, to take Water; when we came there, there was two Boats provided for us, the ſick went all into one Boat and had the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of lying in the Stern; after they had placed themſelves, the reſt of the Men went in and fill'd up both Boats, ſo full that there was not room enough for them all to lie down; yet, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, we could have no reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: after we were all Imbarked, away we went ſwiftly with the Stream, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout eight at Night we came to a Town on the South-ſide of the River, call'd <hi>Blewnack,</hi> where we put aſhoar, here we lodged in two Cellers; the People of this place were ſtruck into a panick fear of us, for as ſoon as we were got into the Cellar they would not let one Man come out to eaſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and many of our Men had the Flux; but when they ſaw that the Door was almoſt broke in pieces by us, they came upon Tearms with us; that was, that we ſhould come out onely one at a time, and ſo when he was return'd then another might come, ſo they went and guarded each Man with three Men, one taking hold of each Arm, and another ſtood to hold the Candle to him, and ſo in this manner they held them out: our Men would fit and laugh at them, and were mightily pleaſed to ſee themſelves ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>erided. Our Supper was a ſmall four <hi>Denier</hi> Loaf and a Cup of Beverage; ſo here we ſlept until Day-break.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Munday</hi> 28. Early in the Morning we went aboard the Boats, the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fair and clear, by Noon we were fall'n down as low as <hi>Burdoon,</hi> there we got our Dinner; which was Bread and Beverage, and one Onion <hi>per</hi> man: From thence we fell down as low as St. <hi>Anns,</hi> at which place we laid the Boats along the Shoar, where they gave us our Supper, which was a Loaf of three <hi>Deniers</hi> or one Farthing Price, with one <hi>Sirdena</hi> and one Onion <hi>per</hi> man; here we remained all Night in the Boats, not having ſcarce room to ſit, and much leſs to lie down; over the after part of the Boat they ſpread the Boats-Sail, which was ſo thin, that if any Rain had fallen it would have ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified no more, in compariſon, than a Cobweb; and as for all thoſe which lay before the Maſt, they had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all over them but the Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Canopy, which was very cool and ſharp.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tueſday</hi> 29. About ſix in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, before the Boat put off, they fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved our us Dinner, (which was) a Loaf of three <hi>Deniers</hi> Price, with about an Ounce of naſty ruſty Pork, and a Cup of Beverage: From hence we fell down as low as the Town call'd <hi>La Port,</hi> which was about Eight of the Clock at Night; as we went out of the Boat every man received a Loaf of ſix <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niers,</hi> and one <hi>Sirdena;</hi> and when we were got into the Stable, where we were to lodge, they gave each man of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:96857:24"/>us a Cup of ſpecial good Wine: ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we had ſupt we went to ſleep in the Stable, it being very cold.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wedneſday</hi> 30. Early in the Morning, before the break of Day, we came out of this Stable, and ſo went aboard the Boats, the Morning cold and foggy; as ſoon as we were ſtow'd the Boats put off, and ſo down we went to the Town of <hi>Marmanda,</hi> the Boats put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoar here to get Bread: our Dinner they ſerved us here, which was a piece of Bread and about three quarters of an Ounce of ruſty fat Pork, with Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verage as at other times. After we had dined the Boats put off, and down we went to a Town on the North-ſide of the River, call'd <hi>Runae;</hi> at this Town we went all aſhoar, and as we went out of the Boats we were ſerved with Bread; ſo into the Town we went, and becauſe the Stables here were full of Soldiers Horſes, they lodged us in a Colledge, or a School; here they gave us Wine to our Bread, our uſual quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity: our Lodging, for the major part of us, was on the cold Stones; but to our ſick. Men they gave a little Straw too. Here being in this Town now a great many Soldiers lying upon free Quarters, two of them, being <hi>Germans,</hi> came to ſee us: It ſo happened that we had a <hi>German</hi> amongſt us, who was not only one of their Country-men, but was alſo born in the ſame Town where one of theſe two Men was born, after ſome mixed ceremony was paſt between them, both of Joy and Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, the one for Joy to ſee the other alive; and the other with Sorrow to ſee his Country man in ſuch a miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſtate; he asked of his Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man how he came to be in Arms for the <hi>French</hi> King? (he thus replied,) Out of the deſire I have to be in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many;</hi> for, ſays he, when it is Spring we ſhall be drawn out to go againſt the Emperor, and then my deſign is to make my eſcape home. He told his Country-man, that when the <hi>Imperial</hi> Forces lay againſt <hi>Buda,</hi> that he and ſeveral other, being Scouts, were taken by the <hi>Turks,</hi> and ſo carried to <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> and from thence ſent to <hi>Smyrna,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Scanderoon,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Grand Cairo,</hi> and from <hi>Grand Cairo</hi> they came down to the Sea-ſide, to Imbark for <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> but in their way they were happily met and took by a <hi>Malteſe</hi> Gally, and ſo got his freedom. Afterwards he came over into <hi>Spain,</hi> and there he liſted himſelf in the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Army, and was in the Army when the <hi>Spaniards</hi> gave the <hi>French</hi> that Defeat I ſpoke of before: and told us the number of Men in each Army, and of the great loſs the <hi>French</hi> had. After we had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken our leaves of them both, we went and laid down to ſleep, but what with the coldneſs of the Stones, and of the Weather together, we were forc't to walk all Night long to keep our ſelves warm.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thurſday</hi> 31. Early in the Morning, by the break of Day, we went aboard the Boats, making no ſtop, but as ſoon as we were all aboard put off, ſo down we went towards <hi>Langoon,</hi> the Morning very cold and foggy; when we came oppoſite to <hi>Langoon</hi> they ſerved us our Dinner, (which was) a piece of Bread and one Onion, with a bit of Pork like the former, and a Cup of Beverage, making no ſtop with the Boats at all; by that time it was Night we came to a Town on the North-ſide of the River call'd <hi>Poeno;</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:96857:24"/>Here we came to an Anchor; but we remained in the Boat all night in great miſery, for want of room, and by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Cold. Our Supper was a piece of Bread and one Head of Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <hi>per</hi> man. The Night was very foggy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>November, Friday</hi> the Firſt. About eight in the morning it was here High-water, and preſently after we weighed, and about eleven of the clock we came down as low as <hi>Burdeaux:</hi> The Boats were brought to an Anchor here, a good ſpace off the Shore, very near oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to the middle of the Town. They ſerved us our Dinner here, which was a ſmall piece of Bread and about an ounce of fat Pork, with a Cup of ſour Beveridge. For all that Wine is ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream cheap here, yet could they not afford us any thing elſe but ſour Stuff, and the meer Lees and Traſh. Many People came off in Boats to us; but the moſt part came to ſcoff at us. We were told here, That all our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants were gone home that lived here. We remained in theſe Boats un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til about five in the Afternoon, about which time we were put aboard of three <hi>Burtoons,</hi> in order for our Paſſage to <hi>Roan.</hi> Our Supper was a piece of Bread and one <hi>Sirdena per</hi> man, with Beveridge; and our Lodging was on the Stone Ballaſt; ſome had a little Straw to lie on, but very few.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturday,</hi> 2. This morning we had the Wind Eaſterly, and the Weather fair; and this morning died <hi>Edward Davis</hi> of <hi>Boſton</hi> in <hi>New-England.</hi> About ſeven of the clock we were under Sail, and fell down about three Miles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>Blois;</hi> at the laſt quarter of the Ebb our Boat ran aground there, and there we lay until the firſt of the Flood: The other two Barks kept far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the Southward, and went clear. As ſoon as we fleeted away, we ſtood galing a head upon the Tide; about High-water the Wind began to freſhen at N.E. ſo away we went briskly: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout eleven at night we came down to <hi>Roan:</hi> Our Dinner and Supper were both alike, <hi>viz.</hi> Bread and Beveridge, and one <hi>Sirdena per</hi> man; ſo we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd in the <hi>Burtoons</hi> until morning.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sunday,</hi> 3. In the morning our Guards went aſhore to Maſs, and at their return they gave us our Dinner, a piece of Bread and a <hi>Sirdena,</hi> with Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veridge, as at other times; after we had eat, we went aſhore, the Boats ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dry: They had provided two Carts to carry our Sick men, which came to the Boat ſides. The People of this Place are in general poor Fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Pilots, and the like; but great was their Love and Charity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, whom they relieved with a bountiful Hand, both with Money and Food; but when the Rogues our Guard ſaw it, they drubb'd the poor Women for giving, and us for receiving, for no other reaſon, as I judge, but becauſe the People of this Town are known to be the major part Proteſtants.</p>
               <p>From hence we marched three Leagues, to a Town called <hi>Ogua,</hi> in which Town we were lodged, ſome in a Stable, and the reſt in a Bakehouſe. Our Lodging was on the cold Ground, and our Supper was like our Lodging, a piece of brown Bread and one <hi>Sirdena per</hi> man. We that lay in the Bakehouſe lay ſo cold all night, that ſome of our men made a Fire, and burnt all the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers Tools they could lay hands on.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:96857:25"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Munday,</hi> 4. This day, being the laſt day that the Rogues our Guard expected to have us under their Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, they pretended to give us a very good Farewell; ſo they bought a whole Sheep, which they boil'd, and gave us the Broth amongſt us, and the Meat they carried with them to the next Town, where we were to dine this day. Our Sick and Lame being put into two Carts, away we marched two Leagues, to a Town called <hi>St. Jan Anglia:</hi> the major part of us got into this Town above an hour and half be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Carts came in with the Sick men, by reaſon they were drawn by ſlow-paced Oxen; in the mean time we remain'd in the Market-houſe, where we found ſuch Charity of the Inhabitants as was not expected; for they gave us great quantity of Bread, and Wine, and Butter, and ſuch other things as they had in their Houſes, with a moſt liberal Hand. They told us the Name of this Town was deriv'd from one of our own Country-men, which was a Preacher in this Church, when there was but one Houſe built beſides the Church; and now it is a pretty large Town. They alſo told us, That for a hundred Years together there did not a Popiſh Prieſt preach in their Church. They gave us their Prayers, beſeeching God to bleſs us in our Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings, and proſper our King. Theſe Words they ſpake to us in their own Houſes, privately. I muſt needs ſay this of the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants, That I do verily believe they are the moſt faithful and charitable People that lay any claim to the Title of a Proteſtant upon the Earth. When the Carts came into Town, they ſerved us our Dinner, Bread and Mutton; but very little of the laſt came to our ſhare; not above an ounce <hi>per</hi> man; and there was above twenty of us that had none at all. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we had dined, away we marched towards <hi>Rochfort;</hi> diſtant from hence three Leagues. Juſt as we came to croſs the River of <hi>Sherant,</hi> it began to rain, when the moſt of our Paſſage, eſpecially the laſt twenty days, we had no Rain, ſo favourable have the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens been to us. About four in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon we came into the Town, and ſo into the Priſon, where we found of <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Priſoners to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Four hundred. When we firſt went out of <hi>Rochfort,</hi> we had Two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and when we came from <hi>Toulon</hi> Sixty more, and at <hi>Tolouſe</hi> Six more; and now we had no more but One hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſeventy three, the reſt being dead and ſcattered about the Country.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tueſday</hi> 5. This morning the <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>van</hi> took all our Names that came in laſt night, with the Ships Names we were taken in; alſo two of our Men that were not attentive to give in their Names, were moſt ſorely drub'd. Now I ſhall deſcribe the manner of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon-Diet. In the morning the Men were told out, and to every ſeventh Man a Seal was given to him to go to the Cook, who gave him upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt thereof a Loaf weighing about ſix Pound, and that is the moſt, and a Can of Wine, but more fitly to be call'd Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veridge, for the better half was Water, and the other part ſour Wine; of this we had to the quantity of ſeven half Pints; and at noon were we thus told out again, and theſe Seals given in the ſame manner, to be carried to the Cook, who upon receipt of it gives them a Bowl with about ſeven ounces of Meat, and a Can of Beveridge.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:96857:25"/>Now the Meat was moſt an end either Liver, or elſe Lights or Milts; and if there was any other ſort of Fleſh, to be ſure it ſhould be the worſt that could be had, and that often would ſtink moſt deſperately. The World may very well imagine what good Stuff it was; for it was common for a Man to ſell his whole Days Allowance of Meat for three <hi>Deniers,</hi> and that is but one Farthing: Their Drink they ſold all they had at a Meal for two <hi>Deniers,</hi> and that was thought a great Price; and truly ſo it was; for whoſoever bought any of the aforeſaid Trade at theſe Rates, paid more than it was worth. Their Bread was moſt an end very good, for that was all we had to keep us alive. As for Food at night, they told them out in the ſame manner, giving them a Seal to go to the Cook for Beans and a Can of Beveridge. The Beans were moſt an end Horſe-beans, and the quantity of them was ſo ſmall, for all three fourth parts of it was Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that when every Man got ſeven Spoonfuls, we reckon'd we had large Allowance. I have ſeveral times taken this eſpecial notice of them. Fiſh-days are all one with them as the Fleſh days, only this, they have ſeven ounces of Fiſh for Dinner, and this is the moſt. When they give their full Allowance, they give them to their Fiſh a little Oil and Vinegar alſo; but Fiſh ſoon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſo ſcarce, that they would give us none, ſo the room of that was ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied with Horſe-beans. Every thing here is now ten times worſe than it was before we went for <hi>Toulon:</hi> Our Lodging is upon the baro Floor, many of us, for theſe ſeven firſt days, in which time our Men fell ſick ſo faſt, that ſixty went to the Hoſpital in two days, and but very few came back. The eleventh of this Month they gave us Straw Beds, but nothing to cover us; the Weather now was very cold and froſty. On the 13th of this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant there came hither 120 Men from <hi>St. Malo,</hi> of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation; Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oufft and Roped together; this gave us but ſmall hope of Redemption, when ſo many Men were brought from the Place where the Exchange was to be made. <hi>December</hi> the firſt here came al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo from <hi>Breſt</hi> 130 Men, which did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the <hi>Portſmouth</hi> and to the <hi>Lively. December</hi> the fourth they gave us Blan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets; but after ſuch a manner they gave them, that the better half of the Men had none at all: Some had a Blanket for four, and ſome for fix, and ſome for ten, and to above 300 Men they gave none at all. And moreover, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they divided them among the aforeſaid men in ſuch a manner, yet were the Blankets very near all of a bigneſs, and would not well cover a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove three men; the meaſure of them was about ſix Foot ſquare, and ſix Foot and a half was the biggeſt. The Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther now was very froſty and cold, and for want of Food, Clothes, and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verings, our poor men fell ſick at a ſtrange rate, and died in the Hoſpital, ſeven or eight in a night, and many times more: We had an account one night of twenty one <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> that died in the Hoſpital, beſides many that periſhed in the Priſon meerly for want.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>December</hi> the fourteenth here came eighty four men more, moſt of them belonging to the <hi>Fire-drake;</hi> from <hi>Brest.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Before we went for <hi>Toulon,</hi> we were guarded by the Towns people; but now were we guarded by Soldiers, who like cowardly Rogues did tyrannize o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us at a very ſtrange rate, every pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:96857:26"/>Rogue carrying a great Stick in his Hand, to drub the poor Priſoners at their pleaſure. Many of the ragged Villains, if they chanc'd to be coming along, and were to paſs by us, if there was not a Lane made for them to paſs, immediately would fall to flouriſhing their Sticks amongſt us, laying on about them Threſher-like. The occaſion of all this ſprang from a young fooliſh Fellow, that was their Major, who did moſt deſperately hate all thoſe of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, Fool like, for he knew not what; ſo by that means he tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated all manner of Villany that was acted upon us, both by the Cook and Guards. This ſame Major was ſo Fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, that his Perſon and his Actions declared him more fit to have kept Geeſe upon a Common, than to have had the Command over ſo many Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners.</p>
               <p>About the latter end of this Month there came in here a great many of their Ships, which were ſo full of Sick men, that they fill'd up all their Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, ſo that thoſe few <hi>Engliſh</hi> that were alive, they ſent away to the Iſle of <hi>Ole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roon de Shattu,</hi> where thoſe good People did relieve them with a liberal Hand; and in the Hoſpital they were alſo very kind to them, as it did appear by them at their return. I have heard our Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſay, when they came back, That the People of this Place have taken off their Clothes from their own Backs, and given to them; and the Women have pluck'd off their own Stockings in this cold Weather, to give to ſome of our poor Lads.</p>
               <p>But to return to our Priſon at <hi>Roch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort:</hi> Our Men, by the hard Uſage here, fell ſick ſo faſt, that they preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to make an Hoſpital for the Sick in the Priſon; which when they had brought to the utmoſt perfection, it might more fitly have been termed a Slaughter houſe. I ſhall, as near as I can, deſcribe the manner of it.</p>
               <p>In the firſt place theſe Rooms were an Apartment from the reſt of the Priſon; yet were theſe as ſtrongly fitted with Iron Bars in the Windows, as the reſt; and in theſe Rooms all round by the Walls they laid Straw Beds as cloſe the one to the other as they could lye, and to every Bed was a Straw Bolſter, and one ſingle white Blanket; then to every Bed was two Men appointed, who were laid down moſt an end with all their Clothes on they had, or elſe they could not be warm, their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering was ſo thin; now they lay ſo thick in a Room, that a Room of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Seventeen Foot ſquare ſhould have Thirty eight and ſome Forty Men; their Excrements annoy'd one the other ſo ſadly, that when a Man was newly come out of the Priſon to be laid there, they were almoſt ready to dye with the ſmell: This I ſpeak by my own ſad experience, their Excrements lying open in Buckets; ſo that what with the ſmell of ſome having the Small Pox, and ſome who would foul under them, with the Flux, and ſo by one means or another, there was ſuch a ſtink that cannot be expreſſed by Tongue nor Pen: Yet was not this all their Annoiance, for in the next place was Lice, with which many of the ſick did ſo ſwarm, that I my ſelf have ſeen a Man lye dead, and his Face ſo covered with Lice, that until they were ſwept off I could not diſcern what man it was, although he was my familiar Acquaintance; no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Shift had they here, whatſoever occaſion they had. In the next place, their attendance was ſome of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:96857:26"/>generally either <hi>Guernſey</hi> or <hi>Jer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey</hi> men, who for the coveniency of their <hi>French</hi> Tongue were thought moſt fit; of theſe there were about Six, whoſe buſineſs it was to empty the Buckets, and to help the weak Men to Stool, and to ſerve the Sick with Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als: As for their Victuals I cannot ſay but that it was very good, and the Wine likewiſe, which they gave the ſick men; for truly ſome of their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, who had the chief ordering of theſe matters, were good tender heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men, and would have done more for us if it had lain in their power; poor men the beſt of them was taken ſick, and ſome dyed, ſo at laſt our men had no body to come near them. Here was an account of above One hundred and fifty men that died out of this Slaughter-houſe, not one in five that went there that ever came out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain alive; it was common to ſee Ten or Eleven, ſometimes more and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times leſs, lye dead under an Arch in the open Priſon yard: Then as for their Burial, it was much like their end, for if any of the Soldiers buried them, they would heave them into a hole like a Dog, if they fell on their Face ſo they lay, or if on the Side; and if the Grave did fall out to be too ſhort, as ſometimes it did, that the Head of the man would not go down, theſe Beaſts would beat down their Heads with the Butt ends of their Muskets; the Ground was ſo full of Water, that they were not able to dig above two Foot deep. The faſter and the more our men dyed, the more we were ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannized over by the Soldiers, who would drub us, and put our Men into Irons upon the leaſt occaſion. I ſaw a Man drub'd once by one of theſe Rogues only for letting a Can fall out of his Hand, and afterwards was put into Irons, ſuch Irons as Gally ſlaves are chain'd to at their Banks, where he remain'd for Eight days with nothing but Bread and Water, in a place where they kept their own Countrymen Slaves, ſuch who were Malefactors, for they hang but very few here; if a Man commits any conſiderable Fact, he is ſentenced forthwith to be a Gally ſlave for Seven or eight year; if it be for Theft, Murder, or Rapes, they cut off a Piece of their Noſe, and a piece of their Ear, and ſo burn two Flowerde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luces, one in each Cheek, and ſhave his Head, and ſo he is Condemned to the Gallies for his Life. Their Soldiers that deſert their Colours are ſerved in the ſame manner, and Seamen that leave their Ships. Theſe things I write not by gueſs or hear-ſay, but to my own knowledg and ſight. This is the manner of the <hi>French</hi> Tyrant, who is Coſin to Death (the King of Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors) but yet after all the Law is paſt upon theſe Malefactors, they after that take ſuch methods, to the beſt of their endeavour, to preſerve theſe their Slaves in Life and Health, by giving them Clothes to keep them from cold, good Shooes and Stockings, and good Food to eat, and Covering to keep them warm; and when they are ſick, great care is taken for them in their Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, both for good Bedding, clean Sheets, and Linnen to ſhirt, and both the beſt Food and Phyſick, and careful Women to look after them as is to be be had; which is far different to what we have heard of them, it being quite contrary. I ſhall now mention one more of their moſt horrid Actions to us at the latter end of <hi>January,</hi> which was thus; at this time the Weather was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Tempeſtuous, blowing a meer Huri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cane
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:96857:27"/>of Wind, it ſo happened that a Stone fell off the Houſe top, where there was many laid to keep the Tiles from blowing off, and ſo it was, that this Stone fell near to the Sentry Box, out came the Sentinel, and ſwore that the Priſoners hove Stones out of the Window at him: It now being late, and all the Prifon Doors ſhut, and moſt of the Men aſleep, they came not in that Night, but ſtaid until the next Morning; then they came into the Room, where I my ſelf lay, and demanded of us who it was that hove Stones laſt night out at the the Sentinel; we all proteſted that we were altogether Innocent of the thing, and knew nothing of the matter, which was really ſo: Yet for all we laboured to perſwade them to the contrary, by all the means we could uſe, all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in vain. So forth they took Ten Men out of our Room, I my ſelf was one of the Ten, being at that ſame time very weak and lately recovered of a great Fit of ſickneſs. I being very well acquainted with their Cruelty, did my beſt endeavour to give them the ſlip, which thing I did when we came down amongſt the thickeſt of our Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſo I hid my ſelf: Now they not having any great knowledg of me, I put off my Coat, and altered my ſelf ſo much, that they did not know me when they ſaw me; the other Nine they carried away, and put them into ſuch Chains as the Gally-ſlaves were kept in, until about Night; then in comes the wiſe Major, according to his accuſtomary manner, ſo to him they told their Tale; he comes imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately to the Men in Irons, and bids them confeſs who it was that did heave the Stones, or elſe he would whip eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man that lay in that Room, which were Forty in number; our Men ſtill proteſted that they knew nothing of the matter; then he told them that ſhould not ſerve their turn; ſo he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered one of them to be ſtript naked to the Waſte, and ſo laid down upon the Ploor on his Face, with two Men to hold his Hands; that done, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded a Slave to give him Twenty Stripes with a double ſmart Rope, that cut him in every ſtroke moſt ſadly: That done, he was ſent into the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to us; he told them withal, that he would ſerve them the like, and every Man in the Room, if they did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs. But his Fury ended in this, ſo that the reſt that were in Irons was to be kept there during his Pleaſure; ſo that if they had not taken ſeveral of them out, and carried them to the Hoſpital, they had died there, the reſt remain'd there Fourteen days, and had nothing but Bread and Water; the Man that was thus whipt, his name is <hi>Mathew Milbourn</hi> of <hi>Scarborough,</hi> and came well over to <hi>England</hi> in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <hi>June.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At the latter end of <hi>January</hi> ſeveral of our Men broke the Priſon, and got away, and where there was One got away Ten might, had not a parcel of <hi>Dutch</hi> men, who were well heated with Drink, made ſuch a noiſe that alarm'd the Guard, and by that means were prevented, and ſome of them taken and cut moſt pitiouſly, and put in Irons Legs and Arms, whereof one dyed of the Wounds they gave him.</p>
               <p>About this time we had an Account, that from the Fourth of <hi>November</hi> 89. to the latter end of <hi>January</hi> 90. Three hundred <hi>Engliſh</hi> men had dyed in the Priſon and Hoſpital, beſides a great many <hi>Dutch.</hi> At this time the Proteſtants of <hi>Rochell</hi> ſent both Money
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:96857:27"/>and Cloaths, a conſiderable quantity, to be diſtributed amongſt us, and for ſeveral Weeks together they ſent every Lords day neer Ten Buſhels of good Bread, which was ſhared amongſt us by one Mr. <hi>Hoſea,</hi> who was Interpreter to the Intendant of <hi>Rochefort,</hi> by reaſon they durſt not be ſeen in doing of it themſelves. If I ſhould deſcribe all the Acts of Charity that we have felt from the Proteſtants ſince our firſt being in <hi>France,</hi> would deſerve of it ſelf a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Treatiſe; ſo I ſhall ſay no more but this, that I wiſh all <hi>Engliſh</hi> People, who live under the ſweeteſt umbrage of the moſt wholſomeſt Laws upon the Earth; where the moſt Interlucent Beams of the moſt Holy Goſpel of Chriſt are ſpread abroad; where every Man holdeth in Right and Property all that he poſſeſſeth; theſe People, I wiſh they had but the Charity and Faith as ſome of the diſtreſſed Proteſtants of <hi>France</hi> have.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>February.</hi> The beginning of this Month ſeveral of our Carpenters were by the Pithy perſwaſion of the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter, for their health ſake, perſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to go forth to work upon their Ships, and withal they were promiſed more Victuals, and Twelve <hi>Souſe per</hi> day, which they imbraced, and went out to work; ſo that in a little time they were bravely refreſhed, when as before they look'd like ſo many Objects of pitty, both for want of Food and good Air and Clothes, which now many of them got; ſo they were imployed only in Caulking their Ships upper and lower Decks. Soon after they got a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Seamen to go forth to work as Labourers in the Yard, giving them Twelve Pence <hi>per</hi> day, which was a great comfort to them: This method they uſed, that in a ſmall time they had all the Men by turn out to work. One day they call'd a Liſt of Fifty Men, and two days after call'd another Liſt, and ſo by this method moſt of the Men got a little Money; now whether this working of the Men on this nature were purely for their own Intereſt or no, which I believe it was, becauſe their great Expedition required more Men than they could have; but yet I am ſure that it ended alſo in the Intereſt of our Men, for now our Men were more healthful, and of a better Countenance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>February</hi> the 16th. Several of our Men made an attempt and got over the Wall, but were diſcovered, and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of them taken; about Twenty got away clear; thoſe that were taken were ſorely drub'd; and after all that, they were put into Irons, and faſtned to the Wall, where they lay expoſed to the Weather night and day; their Fare being only Bread and Water, except it were any thing they got from their Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Priſoners: No Men were admitted to come near them, except it were by ſtealth; thoſe that did, run the hazard of being drub'd: this was ſome part of the Majors love to us. Not long after this ſome of our Men found a convenience to make their eſcapes, by cutting through a Wall, and then after lowring themſelves out of a Window Three Stories high; ſo by this means Three and forty of them made their eſcapes; and by the neglect of thoſe that ſtay'd behind, which did not hail the Rope in, they were diſcover'd, and the whole Country allarm'd, and Men ſent every way in the purſuit of them, all Rodes and By-ways, and the Woods ſearcht: ſeveral of them were taken at ſeveral times and places; and as faſt as
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:96857:28"/>they were taken they were brought back and put into Irons, and ſo faſtned to a Wall under an Arch, where they lay in a moſt miſerable Condition: and if they had got no other ſuſtenance but what the <hi>French</hi> gave them, they with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt had the better part of them periſht, if not all. Theſe are the names of ſeveral of the Men that ſuffered in this kind, <hi>William Deacons, Benjamin Guy, James Ingle, John Hutchins, Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Punton, Jacob Williams, James Ellis,</hi> and ſeveral others; and a Declaration was made about the Country, That if any Perſon was found to give entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to any <hi>Engliſh</hi> Priſoner, they ſhould be put in the Gallies. Much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this time they began to Lanch ſome of the Fiſteen Sail of Gallies that were built here, and ſo kept lanching One, Two, or Three a Week, ſo that by the latter end of <hi>April</hi> they were all lancht. Before they lanch either Ship or Gally, this is their method, about a dozen of their Infallible Doctors goes aboard, with their Crucifixes and other Popiſh trumpery to bleſs the Ship or Gally, and when that is done, they are ſure all things muſt needs go well with them. I obſerved this at the lanching one of the two Ships that was built here, whereof one was a Three Deckt Ship of Ninty odd Guns, and the other a Two Deckt Ship of Sixty odd Guns; the leaſt of theſe two, before ſhe was lancht, had a great number of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Prieſts went aboard to give her a thorough Bleſſing, with at leaſt Five hundred People after them: The next day this Ship was lancht, and in her lanching ſhe broke her Scag, and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered the After Part of her Keell, ſo that they had enough to do to keep her above Water; and if with the ſtroke ſhe had not after run over ſome Mud, that filled much of the Rent up, ſhe had without doubt ſunk. Now theſe Ships were lancht long before they were finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their upper Work being built a flote: When they had near finiſhed this Ship, they fitted for the Careen, and ſo hove her down, and cut out Fifteen Foot of the After part of the Keell. Our Men that remained here in the Priſon, and would not go out to work, were by the Intendants Order kept hear to work, wheeling Rubiſh into the Priſon Yard to raiſe it, having Soldiers to be their Overſeers, continually following them which way ſoever they went. One of our Men, named <hi>Thomas Fenwick,</hi> who refuſed to work in this kind for them, the Major and a Serjeant immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately fell upon, beating him with their great Sticks in ſuch a barbarous manner, that it was thought by all the men that beheld it, that they deſigned nothing elſe but to murder the man. After all this, they made him work with the Wheel-barrow ſeveral days toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Slave like; nay, far worſe then Slaves were we treated by them in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry reſpect; for, as for the Slaves, the <hi>French</hi> King alloweth them very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderably for the work they do on Shore, by which they get both good Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als and good Drink; but all the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward our poor men get of them for their work in the Priſon, is nothing but ill Words, and many a blow on the Back.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>March</hi> the Sixth Two hundred of our men were ſent away hence for <hi>Dinan,</hi> in order to be exchanged; this added to us new Life, thinking it might come to our turns once to be Redeem'd of this cruel Place, if it pleaſed God to ſpare us our Lives, when as juſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our hopes of getting clea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was quite worn Thread-bare.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:96857:28"/>
               <p>In the beginning of <hi>April</hi> here came an Expreſs from <hi>Paris,</hi> for the ſpeedy fitting out of Five Sail of Ships of Sixty odd Guns a Piece: but the laſt Ships that went away from this Place carried away all their Seamen, that they had not ſo many left as was able to Rig theſe Ships; ſo that Orders was given by the Intendant that they ſhould take the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Priſoners out of the Priſon, and put them aboard theſe Ships, and make them rig them, which was done accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly; and when ſome of their Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion Officers, with other Soldiers came into the Priſon to us; our Men refuſed to go out at their Command, ſo forth with they drew all their Swords, Cowards-like, and began to lay on; and ſo by force they drove aboard One hundred and nineteen of them, and divided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt theſe Five Ships, where they continued Twelve days, working ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times both night and day; and when they had any time to ſleep, their Lodging was on the hard Deck: their Victuals alſo was very little, but yet they ſaid they gave to them as much as they did to their own People, which by the Deſcriptions of it, is not half ſo much as the King of <hi>England</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth his Men, for Bread is the three fourths of their Proviſion. After they had rigged theſe Ships, they alſo help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to carry them down the River, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Place where they uſed to take in their Guns; one of theſe Ships taking in her Guns with our Men. After this was done, the Captains of theſe Ships ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our Men if any of them were wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſerve either the <hi>French</hi> King or King <hi>James;</hi> they all anſwer'd, they would not willingly ſerve either of them, but that they would rather dye in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, if King <hi>William</hi> would not Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem them. Upon theſe Anſwers they were all of them ſent to Priſon again, and this was all the Reward they had for their work.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>April</hi> 5. here came Eleven hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derd and fifty Gally-Slaves from <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeilles,</hi> who gave us this account, That as they were croſſing the Bay of <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quedoc,</hi> in ſeveral Gallies and Setteſts, they were chaſed by ſeveral Ships either <hi>Engliſh</hi> or <hi>Dutch,</hi> or both; and they were of this Opinion, that if they had had but two hours day light more they had took them every Man; for it ſeems they came up with them ſo fairly, that they took the Stern of moſt of them which were laden with Proviſions for the Slaves, ſuch as Clothes, and Covering, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This gave ſuch encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to the Slaves, that they did not fear to ſay before the Face of their Patroons, that they did not doubt but that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> would ſet them at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, if ever they went out to Sea in their Gallies. The major part of theſe Slaves were <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Moors,</hi> and the reſt were <hi>French</hi> men. The <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Moors</hi> had alſo Contracted, that if ever they came but near an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Man of War, they would do their utmoſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to give the Gally away to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> in hopes thereby to get their freedom: But I rather think theſe Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies will not venture to go out in theſe Sea, but rather keep them in Harbour on purpoſe to plague his poor Subjects up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every ſmall Offence. Theſe Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies are much leſs then the Gallies in the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> Seas, but in Form al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together like them, being about One hundred and twenty Foot long, and about Eighteen Foot by the Beam, and not above Seven Foot deep in the Hold, which when they have all their Men, and other Proviſions aboard,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:96857:29"/>they will be ſo deep, not above Two Foot from the Water edge in the Midſhips, only their Oars and Banks lye higher above the Body of the Gally, as is their manner ſo to do. Theſe Gallies carry Four Guns right for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in their Prow, and in the Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips right forward in time of Service they have a Cuſhe Piece of about Six thouſand weight, which runs in a Trunk, and ſo lyes when Service is done near the Maſt for Ballaſt. Theſe Gallies that were here built at <hi>Rochfort,</hi> will Row with about Fifty four and Fifty ſix Oars a piece, having ſix Men to an Oar; ſo that theſe Gallies will carry Three hundred thirty ſix Slaves, beſides Seamen and Soldiers, which will be very near One hundred and fifty more. I am clearly of Opinion, that if they come out into the <hi>Biſcayan</hi> Seas, which they muſt of neceſſity do if ever they come out, they will not find them like the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> Seas; and if there doth but blow any Gale at all conſiderable, without they can im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately get into a Habour, the Sea muſt be their Graves, for I am ſure that theſe Gallies will not be able to endure any Sea at all.</p>
               <p>Juſt about the time aforeſaid, we had ſix of our <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> brought here, which were taken as they were ſtriving to make their Eſcape, in this manner: They were in the Hoſpital of <hi>Oleroon de Chattu,</hi> and when they were ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what recovered of their Illneſs, they did their endeavours to get for <hi>England;</hi> and watching an Opportunity to get a Boat, which they had one night, they went away, rowing along the Shore ſide, thinking to meet a ſmall <hi>Burtoon</hi> laden with Wine and Brandy, and ſo to clap her aboard, &amp; then car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry her away for the Coaſt of <hi>England;</hi> but, poor men, on the contrary, they met a Privateer, who chaſed them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhore in the River of <hi>Burdeaux,</hi> at a Town called <hi>Roan,</hi> where they were ſeiſed, and ſo ſent hither, and put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chains, in the open place where they uſed to put the other men that I mentioned before. Four days after theſe men were taken, there came the <hi>Scrivan</hi> of <hi>Oleroon,</hi> to inquire of them who it was that helped them to the Boat they got away with: They told him, No body; for they took the Boat without the aſſiſtance of any one. Now in this Iſland of <hi>Oleroon,</hi> as there are many Proteſtants, ſo, amongſt the reſt, there is a very wealthy man, who uſed to extend the utmoſt of his Charity to our <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> for which he was hated by the other Party moſt deſperately. Now this <hi>Scrivan</hi> would fain have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded theſe men to confeſs, that it was this Proteſtant that helped them to the Boat to make their Eſcape; for they needed no more for the undoing of this good man, but only to have this laid to his Charge: But the men ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly denied the thing, and notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all his Threatnings, they told him, they would not ſpeak againſt their Conſciences, to the undoing of any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent man. The <hi>Scrivan</hi> ſwore by all his Gods, That he would make them confeſs that it was that man, or elſe he would burn them with lighted Matches betwixt their Fingers and Toes: Now whether he did ſo to them or no, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell; for the next day I came away, with two hundred more, in order to be exchanged.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>April</hi> the twenty ſecond in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, before we marched, the good Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>people of this place gave two hundred Shirts to our men that were to march to day, the moſt of them being new.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:96857:29"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>From</hi> Rochefort <hi>to</hi> Denan, April 22. 1690.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>TUeſday,</hi> About Eleven in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 200 of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi> Nation were call'd out of the Priſon, in order for a march for <hi>Denan,</hi> to be exchanged as they told us: juſt before we march'd, they gave us a bit of Bread and a cup of Beverage <hi>per</hi> Man: that done, away we went with great Joy, leaving behind us of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men, in Priſon and in the Hoſpital, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout One hundred and forty or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts: the Morning was rainy, and by that the Ways dirty, but the After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon proved favorable and fair. Juſt as we came without the Town<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, we gave the reſt of our Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, which we left behind, three Cheers or Hollows: That done, away we march'd Six Leagues, to a Town call'd <hi>Lazerean,</hi> leaving <hi>Rochel</hi> on the left hand. About two Leagues off this Town was lately a Town where re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſided much <hi>Proteſtant</hi> People; but, alas, all the Remains that is to be ſeen of them now, is to ſee their Houſes, which are many of them pluck'd down to the Ground, with their Churches al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo: they quarter'd us all here in one empty Houſe, where the Floor was ſpread with Ruſhes: our Supper was a piece of Bread and one Sirdena <hi>per</hi> Man: the inhabitants of the Town gave us Wine to our Supper.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wedneſday</hi> 23. By ſix in the Morning we were all drawn up in a ſquare Place to be counted, and to be ſerved our Dinner; and while we were at it, we heard a ſmall Hand-Bell tinkling, preſently appeared a young Man car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying a Crucifix, after him a great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of poor Men bare-headed, ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome of their <hi>Popiſh Canticles:</hi> after them followed a Man bearing a white Flag, in the manner of an Enſign of War; and after him, an other bore a Flag of red colour, with a croſs in it like that of St. <hi>Georges;</hi> but it was thus carried, the Flag was made faſt to a Staff juſt the breadth of the Flag, and in the middle of the Staff was a piece of Line made faſt, and ſo made faſt to the end of another Stick, ſo it hung like a ſquare Sail: After this followed the Prieſt in his Pontifical Habit, and after him a whole drove of Women; who, as far as I could perceive, minded us more than their Devotion: I did admire, that I ſaw but one Vulture a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all theſe Geeſe, for I always obſerved that theſe ſort of Foul moſt an end goe in flocks. After we had eat a piece of Bread and a Sirdena, and drank a cup of poor ſorry Wine, away we march'd for the Town of <hi>Maraine,</hi> diſtant five Leagues, the Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fair and clear, and the Road good. When we came into the Town we were put into a great empty Houſe, where our Lodging was on the Floor; but ſome of us got a little Litter out of the Stable, but moſt none at all: our Supper was a piece of Bread and one Egg, with a Cup of Beverage.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thurſday</hi> 24. About ſix in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we came out of the Houſe, and as we paſt out they gave each Man a ſmall Loaf, and ſo we ſtood in two-Ranks to be ſerv'd Drink, which was a Cup of Beverage. Here many of our People receiv'd much Charity of ſome of the tender Sex, who gave ſome of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:96857:30"/>us Stockings and Shirts: That done, away we went into three Boats, and ſo was carried up the River of <hi>Maraine</hi> three Leagues, and were landed at a Town call'd <hi>Pouray;</hi> from thence we march'd five Leagues to a Town call'd <hi>Terray,</hi> the Weather fair and clear, and the Road good: When we came into this Town it was quite dark, ſo we were throng'd all into a Barn, where our Lodging was very bad, and our Supper very ſlender, <hi>viz.</hi> a piece of Bread and one Egg <hi>per</hi> Man.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Friday</hi> 25. About nine this Morning they gave us our Dinner, a Souſe-Loaf and about 50 Eggs for two hundred Men, with a Cup of ſowre Wine: That done, away we march'd ſix Leagues, to a Town call'd St. <hi>Vincean,</hi> here they gave us a half Souſe-Loaf <hi>per</hi> Man, with one Egg and a Cup of ſowre Wine; and as for our Lodging, we were all throng'd together in a Stable.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturday</hi> 26. About ſeven in the Morning they gave us our Dinner, a ſmall brown Loaf, worth eight <hi>Deniers,</hi> with one Egg and a Cup of ſowre Wine, ſo away we march'd ſix Leagues to a Town call'd St. <hi>Georges,</hi> the Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther very fair, and the Road good, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all very good Champion Land in this part of the Country. At our arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val into the Town we were conducted into a great Barn, and ſome into a Stable, where our Lodging was very cold in the Night; our Supper was a ſmall brown Loaf and one Egg <hi>per</hi> Man, with a Cup of ſad ſorry Wine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sunday</hi> 27. After our Guards and Provo had been at Maſs they gave us our Dinner, which was ſuch as our Supper, a ſmall brown Loaf and one Egg, with a Cup of ſad ſtuff of Wine After we had eat and drank, away we march'd four Leagues, to a Town call'd <hi>Egreville;</hi> the Way being very good, but the Day very calm and hot. When we came into this Village, we were quarter'd at the ſame Houſe we were quarter'd at in our paſſage to <hi>Rochfort,</hi> at the Sign of the three Kings; our Lodging was in a Stable, our Supper was a ſmall Loaf and one Egg <hi>per</hi> Man, with a Cup of poor Wine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Munday</hi> 28. About eleven in the Morning we were all ſerved our Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, a ſmall Loaf, with one Egg and a Cup of ſowre thick Wine: that done, away we march'd four long Leagues, to the City of <hi>Nantes;</hi> when we came into Town we were put into a cloſe ſtrong Priſon, where we were moſt deſperately throng'd; and our Supper was Bread and Eggs, as before, with the like Drink as before. We heard that the Captain of the <hi>Portſmouth</hi> was kept here cloſe Priſoner.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tueſday</hi> 29. About eight in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we were ſerved our Dinner and Breakfaſt all under one, as they uſed; but now they gave each Man two Eggs and a ſmall Loaf, with a Cup of Wine; the Morning was rainy, and ſo it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued until about three in the After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon; yet notwithſtanding we march'd ſeven Leagues through all the Rain, ſo that we were the moſt part of us as wet as well we could be, and at the end of ſeven Leagues we came to alone Inn, where we had very cold enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment, nothing but Bread and Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and very bad Lodging.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wedneſday</hi> 30. About ſix in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we march'd four Leagues to a Town call'd <hi>Noſce,</hi> where we remain'd
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:96857:30"/>all Day, we lodged in the very ſame Houſe we did when we went for <hi>Roch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort;</hi> the Afternoon proving very rainy. They gave us here a piece of Bread and a little bit of Butter, ſo we remained in two Stables. At Night they gave us the Fleſh that they had long promiſed, about a pound for ten Men, and that was the moſt, yet Meat was very rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably cheap in this place: they gave us to drink ſome naſty foul Cyder; I ſhould chuſe rather to drink Water than it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>May, Thurſday</hi> the Firſt. The Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in being Rainy we continued here un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til about ten of the Clock, about which time the Weather began to clear up: then were we ſerved our Dinner, juſt ſuch a quantity of Meat as before, as near as could be gueſt at, with the ſame ſort of Drink. From hence we march'd ſeven Miles, to a Town call'd <hi>Dervall,</hi> and there we ſtopt an Hour or thereabouts; and from thence we march'd five Miles to a Town call'd <hi>Fuſhgecea.</hi> Here was a great Fair of Cattle in this Town: and this Day we were carried through the Fair, and ſo put into two Stables; our Supper being a ſmall Loaf and one Egg, with Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, our Lodging on the cold Ground.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Friday</hi> 2. About eight in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we were ſerved our Dinner, a Loaf and one Egg <hi>per</hi> Man, with a Cup of foul naſty Cyder; ſo away we march'd three Leagues, to a Town call'd <hi>Beant,</hi> and from thence to a poor Village call'd <hi>Polonia,</hi> one League and a half further; the Weather was ſhowry to Day, but the Road indifferent good, the Land very hilly, but all the Hills very fertile; our Lodging in this place was very hard, lying in an open Barn on the bare Ground, the covering of the Barn was quite gone on the one ſide; our Supper was a ſmall Loaf and one Egg, and Water for Drink.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturday</hi> 3. About eight in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we were ſerved our Dinner, which was a ſmall Loaf and one Egg <hi>per</hi> Man, with Water; ſo away we march'd ſix Leagues, to the City of <hi>Reens,</hi> where we lodged, ſome in an empty Barn and ſome in Stables: Our ſupper was a piece of Bread and one Egg <hi>per</hi> Man, and Water to drink; ſo we lay ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of us like ſo many Pigs in a Stye.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sunday</hi> 4. About eight we were ſerved our Dinner, <hi>viz.</hi> a ſmall Loaf and one Egg <hi>per</hi> Man; ſo away we march'd four Leagues and half to a Village call'd St. <hi>Chapell,</hi> but by the way Three of our Men deſerted us. After they had given us our Supper, which was a ſmall bit of old <hi>Iriſh</hi> ſalt Beef, with a Loaf and a little ſowr Syder, they began to miſs thoſe Men: by this means we were all call'd out into the Cloſe to be counted, and after many times counting, they miſt Three of their number; but good lack, what a toſs was <hi>Jack Provo</hi> in, and his Hounds ſwearing and curſing. Theſe Men were Two of them <hi>Guernſey</hi> or <hi>Gerſey,</hi> and the other an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Man that they miſt; after this we went to ſleep in the Stables.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Munday</hi> Five. About Nine in the Morning they gave each Man about an Ounce of old <hi>Iriſh</hi> Beef, with about half a <hi>Souſe</hi> worth of Bread. From hence we marched ſix long Leagues to the Town of <hi>Denan:</hi> about Four in the Afternoon we came into the Town,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:96857:31"/>where we ſaw many <hi>Dutch</hi> Priſoners, and this day they cleared Thirty ſix <hi>Engliſh</hi> Priſoners. After we were rang'd in the <hi>Praid,</hi> and counted, we were call'd over by our names; that done we were put into two cloſe Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, 100 in a Priſon, where we got neither bit nor ſup for Supper; in the Priſon we found ſeveral ſmall heaps of Straw, on which we ſlept, our hopes of getting clear was our greateſt comfort.</p>
               <p>In this Priſon of <hi>Dinan</hi> were we kept for twenty days, a hundred of us in one Priſon, and the other hundred in another Priſon. In the one of theſe Priſons we had the benefit of a little freſh Air, but in the other none at all, both of them being miſerable ſtinking places, under Ground, in old Caſtles, whoſe Walls were fifteen Foot thick, and the Windows treble barr'd; yet for all this place was ſo ſtrong, they kept Centinels within the Priſons night and day, for fear we ſhould break Priſon; and every day the Officers came and counted us, for fear leſt they ſhould loſe ſome of us. The Wall of this Place was ſo thick, that the Priſon was very cold, conſidering the time of the Year. For our Lodging they gave us Straw, and as for our Food, it was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well, conſidering the place we were in, being far better than any we met with yet in <hi>France;</hi> and our Liquor was only Water. Thoſe People that guard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us here were very civil, not abuſing any of us, as they had done in other places: Our greateſt Annoyance in this place was the horrid ſtink of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which did not only offend the Noſe, but make the Eyes ſmart alſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>May</hi> the 24th. Mr. <hi>John White,</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of the <hi>Betty,</hi> being employed by the King to fetch and carry Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of War, came here to day, and with a great deal of Prudence and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actneſs brought over a hundred and five <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> ſupplying ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them with Money according to their preſent Occaſions, giving them, whilſt they were in their Paſſage, the beſt of Food, and good Drink, and by God's aſſiſtance landed us <hi>May</hi> 31. at <hi>Weymouth;</hi> where when we came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhore, we were kindly treated by thoſe good People. <hi>June</hi> the firſt we got our ſeveral Paſſes of the Mayor; ſo away we travelled to <hi>Dorcheſter,</hi> where we were relieved by the People, the Mayor alſo giving us his Charity very liberally; and at night we got to <hi>Blan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> where we were very charitably relieved by the good People of the Town: But in all the reſt of the Towns we came through, our Men had ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Charity beſtow'd on them, that if ſome of us that had Money had not reliev'd them, they had without doubt died on the Road.</p>
               <p>When we came to <hi>Salisbury,</hi> thirty of us went directly to the Mayor, and ſhewed him our Paſſes; who gave a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us all four ſhillings: Our Men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired his Worſhip to conſider them, they having eaten nothing all day, and as for this Money, they knew not well what to do with it: He haſtily replied, <hi>Give it me again, and I will give you no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing:</hi> So away they went with that little they had. Now this Mayor of <hi>Salisbury</hi> had a Son that was taken by the <hi>French,</hi> and travell'd with us up from <hi>St. Malo</hi> to <hi>Toulon</hi> in Irons; and when we came back to <hi>Rochfort,</hi> died in a moſt lamentable condition with the Small Pox. There were in our Company two Men that belonged to the Ship this Mayor's Son did, whoſe Names were <hi>Samuel Weſtmore</hi> and <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Dicas;</hi> and theſe men had taken
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:96857:31"/>care of this young man in his Sickneſs, and when he was dead, made his Grave, and buried him: Now they had often heard him in his Life-time ſay, That his Father lived well and in good faſhion in <hi>Salisbury;</hi> and it ſo hapning as they came through this Town, they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired for one Mr. <hi>Phelps;</hi> the People told them that Mr. <hi>Phelps</hi> was the May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or; ſo away they went to him, expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting to be ſure a Belly full of Victuals. They told him they came out of <hi>France,</hi> and that his Son <hi>Charles</hi> was dead: He asked them what Ship he did belong to: They told him the Ships Name and Commander too. Well, ſaid he to them, I do believe your Teſtimony, and withal gave betwixt them two a Dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Stiver, and diſmiſs'd them; now I heard the Men ſay, that the People of that Town would take it for no more than a Peny.</p>
               <p>By God's aſſiſtance the major part of us got into <hi>London</hi> the fifth day of <hi>June.</hi> So here is the End of my hard Travels; which as it is not the full Sum of our Sorrows, ſo I am able to produce the Teſtimony of at leaſt twenty Men, in a ſhort time, if occaſion required, that are able to make Oath, that I have not writ any thing in this whole Work that is contrary to Truth. So I wiſh all good People good Succeſs in their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Employments.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:96857:32"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books Printed for</hi> Richard Baldwin.</head>
            <p>THE Memoirs of Monſieur <hi>Deageant;</hi> containing the moſt ſecret Tranſactions and Affairs of <hi>France,</hi> from the Death of <hi>Henry</hi> IV. till the Beginning of the Miniſtry of the Cardinal <hi>de Richlieu.</hi> To which is added, A Particular Relation of the Archbiſhop of <hi>Embrun</hi>'s Voyage into <hi>England,</hi> and of his Negotiation for the Advancement of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholick Religion here; together with the Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi>'s Letters to the ſaid Archbiſhop, about the Progreſs of that Affair: Which hapned the laſt Years of King <hi>James</hi> I. his Reign. Faithfully Tranſlated out of the <hi>French</hi> Original.</p>
            <p>The Cabinet Open'd: or, The Secret Hiſtory of the Amours of Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> with the <hi>French</hi> King. Tranſlated from the <hi>French</hi> Copy.</p>
            <p>The Hiſtory of the Moſt Illuſtrious, <hi>William,</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange:</hi> Deduc'd from the firſt Founders of the Ancient Houſe of <hi>Naſſau:</hi> Together with the moſt conſiderable Actions of this preſent Prince. <hi>The Second Edition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Collection of Fourteen Papers, relating to the Affairs of Church and State, in the Reign of the late King <hi>James.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Character of a Trimmer. His Opinion of I. The Laws and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. II. Proteſtant Religion. III. The Papiſts. IV. Foreign Affairs. By the Honourable Sir <hi>W. Coventry.</hi> The Third Edition carefully Corrected, and cleared from the Errors of the Firſt Impreſſion.</p>
            <p>An Impartial Relation of the Illegal Proceedings againſt St. <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> Colledge in <hi>Oxon,</hi> in the Year of our Lord 1687. Containing only Matters of Fact as they occurred. <hi>The Second Edition.</hi> To which is added the moſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Paſſages, omitted in the former. Collected by a Fellow of the ſaid Colledge.</p>
            <p>The Abſolute Neceſſity of ſtanding vigorouſly by the preſent Government: Or, A View of what both Church-men and Diſſenters muſt expect, if by their unhappy Diviſions, Popery and Tyranny ſhould return again.</p>
            <p>The Juſtice of the Parliament, in inflicting of Puniſhments ſubſequent to Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders, vindicated; and the Lawfulneſs of the preſent Government aſſerted.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:96857:32"/>
            <p>An Account of Mr. <hi>Parkinſon</hi>'s Expulſion from the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> in the late Times; in vindication of him from the falſe Aſperſions caſt upon him, in a late Pamphlet, intituled, <hi>The Hiſtory of Paſſive Obedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The way to Peace among all Proteſtants; being a Letter of Reconciliation, ſent by Bp. <hi>Ridley</hi> to Bp. <hi>Hooper,</hi> by Mr. <hi>Samuel Johnſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Purgatory prov'd by Miracles: collected out of <hi>Roman-Catholick</hi> Authors. With ſome Remarkable Hiſtories relating to <hi>Britiſh, Engliſh,</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> Saints. With a Preface concerning their Miracles. By Mr. <hi>Samuel Johnſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Seaſonable Diſcourſe, ſhewing the Unreaſonableneſs and Miſchiefs of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition in Matters of Religion: Recommended to ſerious Conſideration. By Mr. <hi>Andrew Marvel,</hi> late Member of Parliament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Revolter.</hi> A Tragi-Comedy, acted between the <hi>Hind</hi> and <hi>Panther,</hi> and <hi>Religio Laici.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Collection of Poems, Satyrs, and Songs, againſt Popery and Tyranny. In Four Parts.</p>
            <p>An Anſwer to the Biſhop of <hi>Rochester</hi>'s firſt and ſecond Letters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Intrigues of the <hi>French</hi> King at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> to imbroil <hi>Chriſtendom;</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd in ſeveral Diſpatches paſt between him and the late Grand Signior, Grand Vizier, and Count <hi>Teckley;</hi> all of them found among that Count's Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers. With ſome Reflections upon them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plain Engliſh:</hi> In Relation to the real and pretended Friends to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy. Humbly offered to the Conſideration of his Majeſty, and his Great Council, the Lords and Commons in Parliament Aſſembled. <hi>The Second Edition.</hi> With a ſhort <hi>Preface,</hi> and an <hi>Appendix,</hi> concerning the Coronation Oath admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred to King <hi>James</hi> the Second.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The New Nonconformiſt:</hi> Or, Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Caſe in Preaching after a Depriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, incurr'd by the Expreſs Words of a Statute: Fairly Stated and Examined. With ſhort Reflections upon Mr. <hi>Cook</hi>'s Sermon, <hi>February</hi> the 2d, 16 89/90. which was Licens'd by the Arch-Biſhop's Chaplain.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Fate of France:</hi> A Diſcourſe wherein it is ſhewed, That by the <hi>Happy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> all the Deſigns of the <hi>French</hi> King for the <hi>Univerſal Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy,</hi> are diſappointed; and the Rational Grounds to believe his Downfal near. In three Dialogues betwixt Father <hi>Petre,</hi> Father <hi>La Chaize,</hi> and two Proteſtant Gentlemen.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:96857:33"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Anatomy of a Jacobite-Tory:</hi> In a Dialogue between <hi>Whig</hi> and <hi>Tory,</hi> occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by the Act for Recognizing King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Great Baſtard Protecter of the Little One.</hi> Done out of <hi>French.</hi> And for which the <hi>French</hi> King put forth a Proclamation, with a Reward of Five thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand <hi>Louis d'Ors,</hi> to diſcover the Author.</p>
            <p>A True Narrative of the Murthers, Cruelties and Oppreſſions, perpetrated on the Proteſtants in <hi>Ireland,</hi> by the Late King <hi>James</hi>'s Agents, ſince his Arrival there. Publiſhed for the Information of the <hi>Jacobites,</hi> that endeavour his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn again.</p>
            <p>Reflections upon a Form of Prayer, lately ſet forth by the <hi>Jacobites</hi> of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> and of an Abhorrence, rendred by the Late King, to ſome of our Diſſenting Biſhops, upon his preſent Majeſty's Landing.</p>
            <p>A Sermon preach'd before the High-Court of Parliament at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> on <hi>Sunday</hi> the 27th of <hi>April</hi> 1690. And publiſhed by their Special Command. By <hi>George Meldrum,</hi> a Presbyterian Miniſter, and till of late one of the Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Clergy of that Kingdom.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:96857:33"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
